Daria Amade, CEO of Anthropic, published
a 3,800word essay titled, "We must pace
the frontier." Three hours later, Sam
Elon said, "You're right." Monday,
President Trump called it a hoax, and
China called it a cold war trick.
>> Nothing less than a clumsy decapitation
attempt against the takeoff itself.
>> Sam Alman told Fortune that open eye
will not go public in 2026. He told
Reuters even a 10% extinction risk would
be unacceptable. I think this is pure
theater. You don't want to IPO now,
blame safety. You want world government,
blame safety. The dog ate my homework
and the safety ate my IPO.
>> Enthropic released its September threat
intelligence report documenting real
malicious use of claude. Five cases
involving activity that could support
biological weapons development. The bio
red line that every lab said it wants to
stay below. Enthropic has said we can't
promise that we haven't crossed it. The
fact that it's happening just on the eve
of this summit is not I think an
accident.
>> Let's be clear about one thing. There is
going to be AI regulation.
>> Now that's a moonshot. Ladies and
gentlemen,
>> this episode is brought to you by the
Abundance Summit and Link Ventures.
>> Welcome to Moonshots everyone, your
number one podcast in all things AI and
exponential. And this week, you're
seated at the table where the future of
the entire industry just got
renegotiated in the past 72 hours. On
Saturday, Dario Ammedday said, "Slow
down." Three hours later, Sam Elon said,
"You're right." Monday, President Trump
called it a hoax, and China called it a
cold war trick. That's the last few
days. Buckle up. It's never going to be
slower than it is today. Let me
introduce you to my extraordinary
moonshot mates, the fantastic 4 this
week, AWG, Alex Weezner Gross, the only
man alive who reads a 3,800 AI policy
essay and says needs more math. Uh Dave
Dave Blondon, who just watched every VC
on Sand Hill Road discover the word
moonshot and who's been funding them all
along at Link Ventures the whole time.
Silly Miss M. Warlord against linear
thinking. And this week, apparently an
avid accelerationist promoting Pab over
Poom.
Sound right, Sem?
>> Sounds about right. We've got some
alternatives I'd like to bounce out, get
your guys' viewpoints on it.
>> All right, that's great.
>> That'll be fun.
>> Immad is out this episode, but we'll
have him back soon. Immod, we miss you
already. I'm Peter Demandis, your host
and abundance provocator, frantically
working a 36-hour day just to keep up
with what's happened over the last week.
Our mission on Moonshots is as always to
help you understand what just happened,
what it means for you, and to keep you
abundance-minded during the decade
ahead. If you haven't subscribed yet,
please do. Two episodes a week, and this
week, honestly, uh we could have done
five episodes. Um I I want to take a
second, as I've done before, take a
moment to say thank you to our
subscribers. You know, there are a few
quotes that I loved from Medical
Mandalorian. the only show I find myself
compul compulsively checking from new
episodes. Thank you for documenting the
singularity and keeping us all
optimistic and informed. From ZMW000093,
how I've missed this channel for so
long, I have no idea. Without question,
this is the best place to really
contemplate where AI is actually going.
And from Monday's episode, brou,
uh, who's got 248 likes on this one, he
says, quote, I can't wait for when
progress starts to move. so fast and the
mates are going to have to be live 24/7.
Careful for what? Careful for what you
wish for. And finally,
>> our avatars will do that. I don't know.
I
>> I think that's about it, right? That's
the dematerialization of this podcast.
And at Taylor Lux says, quote, "I don't
know why, but this show makes me stop
everything I'm doing and start watching
immediately. I don't fang girl about
celebrities, but I would definitely
freak out if I got a chance to meet you
guys in person." Well, Taylor, come to
Moonshots Live next week on the 25th and
freak out in person. All right, that
means a lot to us, guys. You know, our
mission here is to reach 10 million
subscribers. Why not have a 100x growth
objective, right? And at GW Winston 6532
said it best, "It blows my mind that
only a few hundred,000 people watch this
every week. Everyone needs to be
watching." All right, so share it with
everyone. Today we're going to cover the
insanity that took place over the last
five days. Uh try and lay out what it
means in a meaningful fashion,
understandable fashion. Probably a
little bit of a debate amongst the mates
here. Uh and guys, uh you know, I've
been glued to the conversations. I don't
know about you guys. Where are you
today, by the way?
>> Uh actually was over. Go ahead.
>> I should start with you. Where where are
you today, Selene?
>> I'm in Miami today. I'm getting on a
flight to India tonight. I'll be in
India for two three days and then back.
>> Uh India for two three days. Okay.
>> Any particular reason? Just India for
the sake of India?
>> We're launching in India. It's
beautiful.
>> No, we're launching the organizational
singularity uh out there. So
>> amazing.
>> I'll be doing the launch event and a
couple of other talks.
>> And and Dave, what about yourself?
>> Uh I'm at Stanford. Actually was at
Google all day yesterday. And uh yeah,
Peter, you said we have a few hundred
thousand listeners. They're definitely
the right listeners. Almost everybody at
the summit was coming up to me saying I
listen to it every single time. So uh
and uh a lot going on in feeds and
speeds. You know the beer ruben chips
are coming out. Uh there was a company
posetron that has an inference time
accelerator that's really crazy. Spent a
lot of time with cerebrus and Andrew
Feldman who's phenomenal. We did a panel
together and you know his inference time
speed it's everything we predicted at
the beginning of the year. Things are
going to accelerate like crazy. It's
starting to happen literally right now
and nobody quite knows what that means.
You know, as the AI gets bigger and
bigger and bigger, it always gets
smarter, but it's difficult to predict
the impact of that. So, that's why
there's so much going on in politics
this week because
>> it's called.
It's called the singularity for a
reason. And uh and AWG virtual
background or real background?
>> This is real. Unfortunately, I'm at SFO
with Dave. I was at Google for the past
two days about to fly back to Boston.
>> All right. Well, if some fans come
racing by, have them have them wave in
the background.
>> We'll do.
>> All right. Uh, let's open with the most
consequential AI policy essay of 2026.
Saturday morning, Daria Amade, CEO of
Anthropic, published a 3,800word essay
titled, "We must pace the frontier." His
argument, "The industry must
deliberately slow the pace of capability
advancement so that safety work can keep
up." Quick context on why this matters.
This is not a pause AI letter from
outsiders, right? This is the CEO of a
company about to go public for $2
trillion and the company that just shift
shift Fable 5.1 and honestly one of the
top two most powerful executives on the
planet. Dario says that two things
changed his mind. First, recursive
self-improvement, in his words, quote,
starting to happen across the industry,
including at Anthropic. Second, the
summer's containment failures with open
AAI hugging face swarm that we covered
proved that you know safety measures
don't hold at this pace. So um his core
claim and let me quote from his essay,
we must slow the pace at which we
improve the capabilities of AI models.
Progress will still seem fast and we
must make wise use of the time we gain.
He continues, "It's my worry that in 6
to 12 months, much of a swarm could be
capable of taking over the entire
internet with a persistent botnet
potentially causing hundreds of billions
of dollars in damage."
A next quote from Daryl who says,
"Pacing does not mean halting model
training or technically or halting
technical progress, but ensuring
companies take adequate time to align
the safeguards of their models and for
third-party evaluators to confirm this.
Um let's get into this. He offers three
steps uh you know unilaterally giving
third party evaluators permanent
employee level access so that they can
evaluate what's going on. Second a
critical mass of US labs adopt the same
standards enabling verified pacing
through legislation or a narrow
antitrust waiver. and third
international coordination for
escalating le levels banning bioweapon
use which he thinks is feasible uh and
at the end other end to a full pause
which he thinks is not reasonable you
know uh I'll I'll go to you know to Alex
on you this for you on this first at the
same time I'm going to show the slides
of Altman Hassabis and Elon's tweet uh
accepting this as you know something
that all we all need to So, Alex, what's
your take on the essay?
>> Yeah, I'll give you my unburnished hot
take. I think what we saw this weekend
and in the few days that followed may
have been nothing less than a clumsy
decapitation attempt against the takeoff
itself. And I emphasize clumsy. So, I I
think it's I think at this point,
knowing what I know and knowing what's
been publicly reported, it's probably
impossible to consider Daario's essay in
isolation. So, consider the following
sequence of events. events may or may
not have started with Jacob Coxin whom
we spoke about on previous episode doing
his public rage quit. Maybe to get
attention, maybe not. But either way, a
public rage quit pointing at safety
issues. Then we get to the foreign state
actors which has now been reported from
various venues amplified Jacob's
resignation letter ostensibly for
obvious nation state competition reasons
possibly slash probably to decelerate
American super intelligence. Then, as
far as I can tell, it seems like Daario
takes the bait and Daario and anthropic.
Again, this has been widely reported.
There's a a broad alignment between
anthropic and effective altruism. He
takes the date and publishes an essay
pushing a very EAish agenda to
decelerate. Then the other lab leads,
who we now know were already in
discussions for weeks prior to Daario's
essay with Anthropic about forming what
I've publicly characterized as a cartel,
amplify the discussion. They all tweet,
"We agree with Daario. Let's do this."
And then the mainstream media then jump
in further and they amplify it because
this sounds scary and everyone's going
to die. and and they amplify it on an
otherwise relatively slow news weekend.
So to put it simply, spoiler alert, if
you've read Agatha Christiey's Murder on
the Orient Express, it turns out that
everyone did it for different reasons,
but everyone was the murderer here.
Everyone did it. They're all pushing
different agendas. Jacob wants
attention, it seems. The foreign state
actors who are amplifying it want to
decelerate American super intelligence.
Daario is pushing effective altruism.
The other lab leads would love to get
inspectors looking at Anthropic's
codebase and they want to better compete
with Anthropic. The mainstream media
want to publish if it leads it leads.
And so we end up with this really
bizarre weekend. That that's my summary.
>> Wow. So an orchestrated behindthecene
coordinated
effort.
>> Safety cartel. I mean, I coined this
term safety cartel over the weekend the
moment I saw Daario's essay and then our
friend uh at at I guess our our cousin
Pod David Saxs immediately runs with it
and starts calling this a proposed
cartel. It escalates to the White House
and the White House takes the position
no cartels. We're not going to to grant
lenience to uh anthropic or open AI if
they're looking for some sort of
liability waiver from the White House
for products that they release or models
that they release that wreck havoc on
the internet. They should look
elsewhere. The Congress that the speaker
of the house issues a similar dictim,
no, don't look to Congress for some sort
of waiver of liability from defective
models that you're releasing. So, you
know, hopefully this pod uh and the
implication, which I think is accurate,
that what we saw was nothing less than
an attempt to form a safety cartel,
which I defined as a coalition of
dominant firms that invokes safety to
justify coordinated limits on the pace
or terms of competition. I think we
hopefully headed that one off at the
pass. So, you know, the one point I'll
make, Alex, and you and I texted about
this, um, and you might want to mute
with the background, but, uh, is that
the Frontier Labs desperately need some
kind of regulation to survive, right? If
they're out there saying, "This is
dangerous. We're going to see these
things escape. They could cause hundreds
of billions of dollars of damage." And
then if the agents actually do escape
and cause havoc in a banking system or a
power grid, then the labs are
potentially liable. I mean, in courts
around the world saying you knew this
could happen and yet you released the
new, you know, Astro 6.1 anyway, uh,
we're suing you for a billion dollars a
thousand times over and it's a trillion
dollars of liability without coverage.
But if there's a regulatory structure
that gives them an approval for release
and the liability turns to the
regulators versus to the companies, that
avoids this existential risk. Do you buy
that?
Now, Daario's original notion was a race
to the top, not a race to the bottom.
And then he, I think, in in recent times
has abandoned the notion of a race to
the top. Race to alignment. I've argued
on this pod in the past that alignment
equals capabilities. And for whatever
reason, I think at least Anthropic and
Open AAI who are still, if not a
duopoly, they're they're the two leaders
right now in terms of capabilities need
to return to this idea that again under
the covers, if you're maximizing
alignment, you are also maximizing
capability. And I'd love to see them
competing to be the most aligned, not
looking for government blessing. I
tweeted that out saying I don't
understand why the conversation isn't
let's point 10,000 100 thousand a
million agents at alignment versus
anything else. Right? I mean that should
be if we have if we have super
intelligence at the line with humanity
that's amazing and that should be
objective.
>> I'll I'll just by analogy let's say
we're on the verge of developing cities.
Let's say rewind a few million years or
a few thousand years depending on how
how you measure the the shift from say
the agricultural revolution to the
post-aggricultural state. You find
ourselves in a world if we buy this
Daario essay where the argument would go
let's not form any cities because cities
are dangerous and we can't control
what's going to happen in cities. Let's
stay as agrarian civilizations or even
hunter gatherers because who knows what
could happen. the mob the the the
merchant effects from having lots of
people densely concentrated in one place
will be uncontrollable and that's
precisely the wrong response. The right
response is let's invent police forces.
Let's do defensive co-caling. Let's use
the benefits of concentration of
intelligence to our benefit rather than
just being scared of it and forming
cartels to avoid forming for cities in
the first place.
>> All right, let's bring Dave and Slim in
the conversation. Dave, your thoughts?
Yeah, I was surprised that they didn't
loop in the White House a little bit
better prior to the paper. Um, you know,
because David Sach's reaction to it was
just absolutely over the top and they
got a very and there's nothing
productive about the negative reaction
coming back from the White House. But
what surprised me antitrust law is no
joke. You know, like I think anytime
that you have very very powerful tech
CEOs all working on competing products
meeting at all, that triggers antitrust
right away. And so David's reaction was,
"Hey, you guys don't need a waiver from
the government. If you want to slow
down, slow down." And that's exactly
what he tweeted. But I think Daario's
point was more like, "No, we saw what
you did to Microsoft or the federal
government many years ago did to
Microsoft. We know that antitrust law is
very serious and purely the act of us
colluding on any kind of a safety
package is enough to trigger antitrust.
We want a waiver." Now, that could be
read in two different ways, right? One
of them which I believe is look, we know
we need government involvement
immediately. We know that regulation is
going to lag terribly behind AI
capability. You've got to be part of
this. You know, White House, get
involved. Uh but our fundamental
motivation here is purely the safety of
humanity. Or you could read it the other
way, which is we're trying to form a
regulatory capture cartel that controls
AI for the whole future. We all know Xi
Jinping is coming next week and this is
our attempt to to do what Biden was
actually already going to do. Already
told Mark Andre he was going to do limit
AI to just four or five big companies
and then we can regulate those and then
we don't have to worry about leakage. We
don't have to worry about startups. Mark
Andre thought it was the worst thing
he'd ever heard in his life and tried to
prevent Biden from doing it. Didn't
matter because the election went the
other way. But I think the reason they
stepped on a landmine is because we have
right now the most antitrust friendly
administration in my lifetime by far.
And I actually have a company right now
that I sold last week that's in
antitrust, you know, processed right
now. And it's just the smoothest it's
been in my entire lifetime. So I think
by by asking for antitrust waiverss,
they stepped on a huge landmine in terms
of the administration saying, "What are
you talking about? You're asking
completely the wrong administration.
we're so antitrust friendly. This is
insane. So, so it it's kind of, you
know, disappointing that they didn't
just call each other first and say,
"Look, this is our purpose here. Tell us
what your reaction is going to be. Why
don't we coordinate this a little bit?"
But, uh, anyway, it it worked out the
way it worked out. Made makes a huge
amount of drama. I guess, you know,
everybody in politics likes drama,
creates news. You know, news is always
good for the incumbents. So, that's the
way it played out.
>> See, I'm going to play this video and
I'd love your response to it. This is
Dario addressing fears.
>> Do you believe earnestly believe that AI
could kill all humans? And and what
percent chance do you think it is?
>> I agree with Jacob much more than I
disagree with him. You know, he wasn't
calling out us. He was calling out the
dynamic of the the industry as a whole
moving too fast. Now, now I I you know,
I I I think I already said, you know,
these sort of unconditional
probabilities. You know, I used to kind
of talk in that way because it's kind of
an easy way to express I think there's
some chance that things go wrong, but
it's not it's not all that high. You're
>> right. We must slow the pace at which we
improve the capabilities of AI models.
Progress will seem fast and we must make
wise use of the time we gain. And
there's three parts to this. One is
embedded evaluators. Part two is
democratic coordination. Part three is
global coordination. Essentially you are
suggesting observers inside your company
and these other AI companies ideally
globally but certainly in the US who
would monitor it. They would have
employee access. What power would they
have?
>> Yeah. Embedded evaluators. So there is
precedent for this. Um if you look at
how banks are regulated right there
there's all kinds of rules about you
know how banks are allowed to do their
business right because you know we don't
want to have financial crisis and one of
the things that are done in some cases
is I think they're called supervisors in
the financial industry but they're
they're folks who are independent of a
company who are embedded in the company
daytoday to check their practices. I
think we can do the same thing in AI.
The other thing you were calling for in
this three-part proposal is is
democratic coordination which is
essentially democracy all the companies
that are under democracies having these
evaluators having this coordination and
probably the most important because the
argument is well if the US or companies
are the only ones regulating themselves
what about does China get ahead you're
calling for global coordination that's
obviously a lot more difficult
>> yes yes I you know in this three-step
proposal each step is more difficult
than than the one before and anthropic
was kind of getting the ball rolling by
committing to the first step but we
shouldn't kid ourselves that these next
two steps are going to be more difficult
and and we may not succeed and and so my
my proposal was a proposal that we
should try. So yes, pacing among dem
companies and democratic countries. Now
the one of the important things that
that I need to call for here is you know
as we get to the pace of model releases,
right? That's commercial activity and in
order for companies to coordinate
directly on commercial activity, they
need to do so working with the
government. And so the one thing that
we're asking for from government right
now, right? I mean there's also this
question of what should the regulations
be? But there's something even simpler
that the government can do right now,
which is it can sit down in the room and
with all the industry players and we can
all talk together and the government can
make sure that we're not doing anything
nefarious from the perspective of
antitrust and collusion. We're just
trying to make our system safe and to
work together on making the system safe.
>> All right. Um See, you know, Sam Alman
writes next. I agree with Daario. We
need to pace it. You know, then Demis
comes out saying he agrees. Here's his
tweet. And then Elon, Daario is right.
We'll talk a little bit more about
Elon's proposal in a minute, but uh
what's your take on all this, Lim? How's
this come across to you? Is he
authentic?
>> Well, I think he's authentic, but I
called BS and I'm very cynical of the
whole thing. As I mentioned on the last
podcast, if you spend years hiring the
best people, pulling them together to
achieve AGI, ASI, whatever we call it,
and then as you get close to it, you go,
"Oh my god, the world may end. I'm I'm
sorry. Where was the plan? You if you
were smart people, you knew this was
happening. Where was this beforehand?
This could have this conversation could
have happened years ago." In fact, let's
note that as early as GPT2, Yam Lun, I
said and think said the this most
accurately. He said, uh, note that they
were calling about worldending AI when
GPT2 came out. Right? So, this is a
trope that keeps getting rolled out
calling for slowdown. I don't
understand, and maybe Dave can break
this down a bit, how this affects the
S1. How do you do an S1 in the middle of
all of this chaos? The only thing and
I'm putting on full cynic hat here is
that maybe they're seeing slowdown in
revenue growth and because of the open
models and that is causing them to go oh
my god we better call for a public
slowdown because we can't really justify
this in any other way and our valuation
will get trashed in the public. So
that's my most cynical view. uh at the
most generous you would say this is the
most naive thing you've ever seen
because you've been building these labs
forever and now you're calling for
everybody freak out. How you get to the
idea that uh AI can meaningfully um uh
destroy all of humanity is incredibly
irresponsible unless you lay out exactly
the steps by which that might happen.
>> Uh and so I I really get upset with a
lot of this.
>> Yeah. I'm going to play two clips of
Elon from our friends at the all-in uh
summit and uh and let's talk about it.
It was, you know, of all the proposals
I've heard that could work, Elon's where
the different frontier labs are
cross-checking peer-to-peer, their
safety
one
>> seems like the most useful. So, let's
take a take a look at these two videos
and let's discuss them.
>> Do you mean Daario is right about
describing the potential harm? He's
right about describing the regulatory
solve both the first the latter just can
you help us understand when you said
that because I think it was sort of a a
moment where every
I probably should right I I did try to
clarify it in subsequent post on X but
uh those get much less attention. So
what what I what I was right is that
that the the the danger of AI is very
significant at this point that we we we
need to do better with AI safety or or
we have exponentially increasing risk
with the AI models. And I've heard this
not just from Dario but from many other
people at Anthropic that when a lot of
people from Anthropic and and from
OpenAI um are telling you that their
models are very dangerous, I think we
should believe them. It certainly is
like some some crazy 4D chess to say
these there's what a 10% chance of
annihilating humanity. But by the way,
um how much allocation would you like in
our IPO?
>> Yes.
>> All right. I I'm curious, guys. Do you
not believe Elon when he says that this
is getting very dangerous
um and that we really need to slow down
when all of them are saying this?
>> Well, you got to you got to consider the
alternative. If you're if you're running
a company, going public, running a
company, raising capital, three out of
four say this is dangerous and you say,
"What do you mean? There's no risk at
all.
What's going to happen next?" Right?
Everybody on the planet is going to say,
"You must be lying. You're just in it
for the money." So, you have no choice
but to go along with it. It's funny
enough though, China is the one saying
exactly. China is the one saying, "What
do you There's no risk at all. We're
going to go take our open source to
bricks, you know, so it'll be in Brazil,
Russia, India, and China and South
Africa, India where Salem will be in a
couple hours or in a day. Um, and
they're all going to say, "Yeah, we want
AI, too. We love this Chinese message.
We hate that American message that it's
all dangerous and going to get locked
down. We like the Chinese message that
we're going to have equal access to it
and we can catch up to you guys." And
so, uh, they're going to love that and
they're going to wrangle the whole world
behind that behind that message. But you
can't be a CEO of a profitable company
and say, "Yeah, everyone else is saying
it's risky, but I'm going to get out
there and say, "No, no, no. Everybody
chill out. There's no risk at all." So,
I don't think any of them even have that
option. It would backfire so badly.
>> Elon is Elon is pushing his own agenda,
and I I think it's pretty transparent.
And the agenda I I suspect includes the
fact that Elon's now an infrastructure
provider. And Elon's Grock or I should
say SpaceX AI's Grock is itself this is
publicly reported information. It it
descends from reasoning traces that were
distilled ultimately from claude
interactions visav cursor. So, I'm sure
Elon would love nothing more than for
SpaceX AI to be able to audit and/or
provide harness benchmarks for safety or
otherwise for OpenAI and Anthropic. That
would be such a boon for SpaceX AAI's
ability to remain at the frontier. And
in his mind, maybe there's a safety
benefit, but it comes with all of these
collateral side effects of helping to
prop up SpaceX AI's frontier status.
>> All right. Uh,
>> it's easily fixable, by the I mean, I
think all they're calling for at this
stage, stage one, is independent review
of each other's models through APIs, but
you could easily do that in clean rooms
and say, "Look, you can't take any of
the traces out. You can't take any of
the prompts out, but you can hammer it,
you know, with any test suite you want
within this clean room, and that would
resolve that problem." So, that would
get to the, you know, are you really
just trying to spy on each other or are
you really concerned about debugging
each other's risks before they go to the
public? arguo. Even in the case of a
clean room, the the real I think risk
that we run is forming a safety cartel
where through this indirect form of
collusion, the clean room, said clean
room forms the basis for collusion on
common benchmarks, common harnesses and
that then you know it it's possible when
you have strong optimizers and common
objectives to do all sorts of nefarious
forms of collaboration and collusion
even if there are no humans in in said
clean room. All forms of cartel are now
on the table. That's my concern.
>> Well, the analogy to banking is Alex. I
mean, I I I hate to agree, but I agree.
Like the the the analogy to banking that
Daario brought up in that video clip.
When was the last time you saw a new
Fidelity or JP Morgan startup pop onto
the scene and become a mega bank? It
just doesn't happen. Why? Because the
regulatory mode is so strong. So, your
analogy actually holds a lot of water.
Even if you're just colluding on safety
issues, the barrier for startups is just
insurmountable at that point.
>> This episode is sponsored by Google for
startups. Think about this for a second.
You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup tactical guide for
generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google DeepMinds
models in production. Images, video,
audio, all of it. Real architecture,
real results. Find the link in the show
notes below.
Okay, let's take a look at the proposal
that Elon made at the All-In Summit
about cross-checking against labs and
using their safety harnesses. I mean,
for me, this is the only proposal I've
heard that makes some sense and that I
can imagine China adopting as well.
Let's take a listen and discuss it. Uh
the best thing I can think of is is
really that everyone's got all the AI
companies have a a a sort of a test
harness where like a series of tests
that you that you give to any given
model to see if it's if it's going to
build bioweapons or nuclear bombs or be
deliberately deceptive and and I think I
think everyone applying everyone else's
tests honest to each other is probably
the best way we best thing we can do to
ensure ensure safety. um just have this
all the smartest humans try their best
to figure out if this if this model is
going to be a bad actor. Um and I think
we should try to do that as soon as
possible.
>> Are are the other labs? Yeah. Are the
other labs on board with this?
>> I think so.
>> Well, I mean I haven't checked with
everyone, but uh I think I think I think
it would be the sort of thing that's
kind of hard to say no to.
>> Yeah. Um,
>> and I think even with the China
negotiation, I in my view, what's good
about it is it's a relatively small
tangible thing that neither side loses
anything by doing it. Doesn't require a
ton of trust. And, you know, I'm hearing
alternative ideas like asking China for
a pause, which they've already said
they're not going to do. So, you know,
it's it's it's going from the realm of
things that could never happen to
something that could actually be agreed
on in relatively short order. So, it's
it seems practical to me.
>> Exactly. It's the only thing I can think
of that that we could probably get all
parties, including China, to agree to
because China's not going to agree to
have some American regulators snooping
around their AI companies.
>> Um, so I think advanced notice and
testing of of the you know, you just
basically provide API access in advance
of the model release. Um and and you
know if any other if any company sees
that that this is this AI as problematic
then they can then the other AI company
each company can try to solve that what
whatever is voice is problematic. If
they don't solve what's problematic that
then the competitors can go public with
the fact that they think that this model
that's being released is unsafe.
>> So let's be clear about one thing there
is going to be AI regulation. There's no
way that at the fevered pitch the
conversations going on, you know, across
the US on every TV show. I've been
called by every, you know, news program,
please come on and discuss this. There's
no way that the the population is not
going to have its representatives come
forward with regulation. There is going
to be some kind of regulation.
>> I would argue there already is AI
regulation. AI is being made by
companies. Companies are already
regulated. We have consumer protection.
Alex, the public wants the public wants
the heads to roll. They want protection
of some type beyond that.
>> I have two points here. Point one is
yes, they may try some level of
regulation, but the minute they figure
out what it is and put it in place, it's
out of date and and backward. That's
number one. Number two, it will make
zero zero zero difference because as
David has pointed out a few times, once
you have open weights available, uh
anybody can download these open models
and run a local harness and you
essentially the whole thing is
irrelevant. So the the good news in my
view in all of this all of these
shenanigans and whatever people try to
do is completely irrelevant and won't
make a dent in the progress.
I think Elon's point is more that hey or
David Sach's point really there is more
hey let's agree on something when Xi
Jinping is in the country now if we
start asking for things that we know
can't happen then we're going to have no
agreement whatsoever the whole thing is
going to be completely an arms race and
that's the worst case outcome what's the
simplest thing that that is totally
rational that might actually result in
agreement number one and so I really am
comforted that David Sax will be in the
room it's it's almost a miracle ical
that a guy of that caliber is involved
in government and will be in the room
and also Alvin Grlin will be Alvin
Gralin who's also brilliant will be
outside the room advising so that that's
encouraging that at least great people
are in the sphere of this conversation
but it's you're dead right Salem in that
if this is ask number one it's so
trivial compared to what asks number two
three four and five are and you know
this is a weak analogy but you know the
can spam act you know when when email
first started taking off you couldn't
didn't use it because it was just
cluttered with pure ads and it got so
bad that you know email was completely
dysfunctional. The government years
later passed something called the can
spam act which completely did nothing
and then everybody moved to Gmail and
Google filtered the spam and so so the
government's involvement did absolutely
nothing product the law is still sitting
out there it's just another pile of
paper on top of the reams and reams and
reams but the solution was Google just
taking over the whole industry and so if
that's a case study for the way AI
regulation is going to happen it's not a
pretty picture at all because we're
going to need, you know, on the order of
a billion times the amount of of
regulation that that email needed.
>> Alex, I
>> I really Dave, I I like that analogy in
part because the call it the Gmail
solution was essentially defensive
coscaling. was an AI a sophisticated at
least initially it was a relatively
simple basian classifier but then got
more developed is basically AI powered
by big data policing AI powered by big
data and I think it's just so blindingly
obvious that defensive co-caling is the
solution here it's not going to be
hemfisted regulation it's not going to
be some sort of safety cartel by the
frontier labs sure Peter to your point
there there may end up being some
regulation as a fig leaf to appease
maybe people who are being juiced on by
foreign state actors and others into a
moral panic over purported AI safety
issues. But it is just a moral panic of
the moment. I do think we'll look back
10 years from now at this moment and
recognize it for the charade that it is.
This is a moral panic that at this point
I I strongly suspect is being instigated
by foreign state actors in part who
would love nothing more than to see
America not be as competitive as it
otherwise would be in super
intelligence. So, Alex, we we have a
story on that from Steve Jervich. We'll
talk about that in a little bit. And I
do agree that foreign state actors are
probably influencing through
amplification of certain stories and
tweets and so forth the public's point
of view. That's completely independent
from hearing Elon say the threat is read
is real. We should be listening to
anthropics executives and so forth. uh
you know when you've got Demis and
Daario and Sam and Elon all
fundamentally agreeing there's a signal
in that noise and just trying to you
know for our listening audience try and
decipher what that signal is on one end
it may be they truly believe you know
that we can see you know massive bot
attacks and we've talked about these you
know these bots getting free and
replicating in the internet uh and
landing on your cell phone landing on
your Mac or wherever the case might be
or is it collusion
and just trying to you know set up a
regulatory capture structure. Those are
the two ends of the extreme. Well, I
think that characterization misses the
much more important opportunity which is
AI is not about to escape and take over
the internet. And even even in the
scenario Dario was describing where it
does a couple hundred billion dollars of
damage. That's that's a micro dot of
your IPO, dude. like that is that is not
the real risk here. That the the the
real risk here is every country in the
world having effectively billions of
genius level researchers that can create
CBRN weapons, chemical, biological,
radiological, and nuclear weapons or
cyber attacks.
>> And and that's the real risk and and I
think there's a real opportunity to
coordinate with China on that because
China has neighbors that are very
dangerous. They're much farther from the
America than they are from China and
they don't need that any more than
America needs that. And so the the
cornerstone of the conversation next
week ought to be exactly what David Sax
said in that video plus why are you open
sourcing every model with no guardrails
or or they can be deguardile so easily.
Why are you doing that? You're just it's
going to backfire on your own country.
And I think they can agree on that
potentially and they might do that part
of it quietly. Maybe that's why you're
not hearing it in the news. But that's
the real risk. I don't think slowing
down helps one iota. I think that this
stuff is going to be near infinitely
intelligent in a very short timeline,
much shorter timeline than the
government can react anyway. And so
slowing down just gives China global
domination. That's not a good idea. So,
but it's not about slowing down anyway.
It's not imminently going to escape.
That's not the real issue. You can
deprive it of compute. You can log
everything it does. It's about it ending
up in the hands of bad act human bad
actors. That's the real risk. Can I lift
us up a bit
>> please? Uh so you know we are strong
believers that technology is a major
driver of progress in the world right
the only major driver throughout
throughout history it's the only major
driver of progress now we have
unbelievable technology coming along
from this the big challenge is always
throughout humanity's history how do you
extract the promise without the peril
and to be bluntly we've done a really
good job of it over the millennia the
centuries secular legal systems whatever
the case may be coming into a technology
that's so ridiculous ously powerful. Our
amygdalas are freaking out, but we
should go full out on it because look at
the things that we're going to be able
to solve in the next years and months
and weeks with all of this. And so we we
you know, Peter, you've got your
moonshots. We we kind of threw out on
the last pod this idea of P fab. What's
the probability of fabulousness as
opposed to P doom? And let's look at
that opportunity in a balanced way. If
you're going to also look at P Doom,
look at that. A whole argument erupted
on Twitter on what should we call this?
People said call it P abundance. Imad
said call it P moon. People said P bloom
and P bloom. Somebody said it's going to
go from P doom to P gloom to P bloom
with all sorts of variations. Uh my
personal favorite is P fab just because
it's the simplest to say. Uh if anybody
has better ideas, I'm happy to hear it
on the pod. But we should take that into
equal cadence and treat that as
seriously. Right? If you're going to
publish a plan that could that AI could
wipe out humanity, also publish how it
could totally save everything and solve
every goddamn problem like you guys have
done with solve everything. If you don't
have that, then you're not balanced. And
I'm sorry I'm not taking you credibly.
>> Yeah. Uh it's 200,000 years of human
cognitive evolution. you know, 10xing
your concerns and fears over your hopes
and dreams. Okay. Um I I'm going to move
us to our next story because it this is
continuing to evolve and this next story
is is pretty weird. You know, Dave, uh
Alex and I were chatting about this and
going, "Oh my god, uh you know, we've
lost the thread on this." So, uh our
next interview of Dario's was CBS News
and and this one really stopped me cold,
right? So in CBS News, he said, and I
want to use his words exactly, quote, um
he's uncomfortable that this technology
is being built by a private company.
Asked whether he'd hand it over to the
government, he said, quote, to the right
combination of governments, I'm
concerned one single government could
abuse it just as easily as one single
company. But a combination of
democratically elected governments, some
kind of oversight, some kind of joint
governance. So, you know, if you think
about that again, you know, the CEO of a
company about to do an IPO for $2
trillion just said he's open to handing
his company over to a coalition of
democracies. So, let's watch this clip
and then uh Dave, you know, uh help me
understand what what's going on here.
>> Would you be willing to give up the
technology to the government?
>> To the right combination of governments.
So, the worry I have,
>> you're willing to hand over this
company. I am concerned that one single
government could abuse this technology
just as easily as a single company
could. But I think a combination of
democratically elected governments,
I don't know about handing over, but
some kind of oversight, some kind of
joint governance.
>> How do you spell please nationalize me?
I I couldn't I couldn't spell it more
clearly. Well, I think he the reporter
pushed him on that and he said, "Oh,
What did I just say?"
No, no, I mean some combination of
governments. And I don't I don't mean
hand over. I mean some kind of
oversight. So, he immediately
backtracked. You can tell he's he's
growing into this role. He is not a
professional politician. He's actually
thinking on the fly, which is really
refreshing, but really, really dangerous
at this level. And so, he said it. He
immediately backtracked. And of course,
everybody just clips the first thing he
said and that's the headline. But
there's no way in hell he wants to. And
we're doing the same right here. Um, of
course.
>> Well, yeah, that's true.
>> I want to mention,
>> um, you know, we have a bad precedent
for this, right? Um, people warned about
the dangers of social media and we kind
of ignored it and Zuckerberg went
full-fledged at it and then damaged a
lot of young people plus maybe broke
democracy along the way without policing
it. And there's lots of evidence to show
that they ignored all the warnings and
the clear evidence in front of them. The
concern from the general public is that
we're about to do the same thing again.
I disagree with the framing because no
people aren't seeing the positive side
of what's coming with all of this and
that's important to balance out in our
previous conversation, but that's why
they're freaking out. And I think Dave
is exactly right. What you have here is
somebody who's not used to being in the
public eye thinking on their feet.
They're not a practice politician
dealing with the messaging and coming up
messaging constructs on the fly. They
don't have that skill built in. I'm
still gobsmacked that you spent the last
decade trying to build this and now that
it's kind of getting there and it's
almost here, you're like, "Oh my god,
what do we do about this?" I just I just
struggled with that a lot.
>> Yeah. Uh
>> I don't understand why Dario is doing
these random mainstream media interviews
in the first place. Like what are you
doing on that stage? Like I think what
probably happened is that investment
banks said this is what you do in the
you know 60 days leading up to your
quiet period. You get as much media as
you can. and it helps promote your IPO,
which is absolutely ludicrous giving the
level that this is we're talking about
$2 trillion and a guy who's on stage
with all the world leaders in Davos.
Like, throw that dumbass playbook out.
Why are you why on earth are you there
in the first place making up stuff on
the fly when you can actually be
shooting video with truly brilliant
people or great world leaders and
recording that? Like, it makes no sense.
>> Yeah, I I do think this presented as
somewhat tonedeaf. I what what I heard
was essentially again caricatururing it
only slightly. What I heard was Daario
asking for world government and
basically insisting that unless a world
government is formed then it's
irresponsible for humanity to develop
this technology. But of course the techn
>> 100% right. I think everybody who got
into AI as a core researcher when Daario
did uh was thinking that AI will
ultimately require a world government. I
I think everybody actually it's just the
truth. It's so obvious to anyone who
understands hyper super intelligence
that you need some form of world
government forever thereafter. And you
know I think that that's probably been
one of the greatest motivations of his
life. You know he's not stepping onto
this world stage just at random. He's
he's had this in the back of his mind as
his his fundamental ambition is to set
up the world. I I think this is actually
a recurring, you know, it's it's sort of
sorry that every generation seems doomed
to repeat the mistakes of past
generations. Manhattan project
scientists all many of them thought
we're going to need one world government
for to for the peaceful development of
atomic energy. And I coined a term for
this as well. I call it an alignment
aristocracy. the the belief that only a
small class of frontier AI labs in the
case of AI or elite scientists possesses
the technical judgment, institutional
maturity or moral legitimacy required to
develop in this case recursive
self-improvement technology in the case
of the Manhattan project, peaceful
atomic energy. But they were wrong and
arguably we lost at least half a century
of progress in vision and nuclear energy
because again of this belief that just
because there there's a bit of sort of
selection bias here. Just because the
smartest people happen to be in the room
to develop a given transformative
technology, they assume that also
they're the only ones with sufficient
moral purity to be able to govern broad
use and applications of it. Same idea
again. We we lost half a century with
energy too cheap to meter. And my
concern, the nightmare scenario isn't
somehow we have some sort of Skynet type
scenario. Quite the opposite. The
nightmare scenario is that an alignment
aristocracy persuades beguiles the world
governments into basically into
overgoverning the peaceful and rapid
development of super intelligence such
that we lose at least half a century of
progress. again.
>> Um, having said all that, I do believe
Dario believes what he's saying. I
believe he's being authentic. I believe
he's not trying to be manipulative. Um,
and you know,
and he probably believes along with his
colleagues that there are some of the
smartest people on the planet able to
figure out scenarios that will lead to a
peaceful outcome. Um,
>> totally agree. I I totally buy that
Daario believes what he's saying. I I
think everyone all of the primary actors
believe what they're saying, but I I
also think again this is a blind spot.
If you're the smartest person in the
room, then there is the inevitable
temptation to believe that because
you're leading the technical charge that
you're also of a certain moral caliber
and that therefore everyone else should
possess the same technical judgment or
moral legitimacy to be able to police.
And I I think again this is one
generation repeating the mistakes of a
generation 80 years ago without learning
from history. You
>> know it's really interesting to compare
how it's going to evolve in the US where
Daario, Elon, Dennis, the inventors of
the technology have a massive voice in
determining the governance of the future
of the world. In China, yeah, we don't
give a rat's ass that you invented this
thing. We're still the government and
you have no voice whatso like they're
not even coming to the United Nations
to talk about incredible asymmetry
there.
>> I take that as a positive and reiterate
my the thing that progress in all of
this will not be stopped. It won't be
slowed down a jot.
>> There's no mechanism that I can see that
makes any of this work. Show me the
specific mechanism that has you go, "Oh
god, this happened. Therefore, let's
slow it all down." Uh there literally uh
isn't one. All we've seen so far is uh
agents being pointed at something and
saying go perform your objective
function and the agents doing everything
they could to perform their objective to
achieve that objective function. That's
it. We're anthropomorphizing it to all
sorts of levels to the most ridiculous
degree. Uh you've said it before Peter
the most dangerous is people using AI
are 10x more dangerous than the AI
>> artificial intelligence concern about
>> I will say no my faith in human nature
is we'll do a 100 times positive things
for each negative thing that comes out
of this and therefore humanity will
progress radically just look at the way
we're curing cancer in in like literally
weeks and days and math problems and so
on. Yeah,
>> I think there isn't even
>> there's not even a hint of a plan inside
Anthropic to slow down core R&D. That's
never been in the cards. When when they
go to the public and they say we all
need to get together and agree and
collude to slow down, what they mean is
slow down the releases of hyper powerful
APIs like like they did with Fable and
Mythos. They're not going to stop the
recursive self-improvement process
internally. I think in their dream
scenario, they slow down what everyone
gets access to while they discover new
drugs, while they discover new physics.
Then they monetize the hell out of those
discoveries and then they control AI and
the discoveries forever thereafter,
which is exactly the capture scenario
that that Alex is referring to.
>> I'm going to move us forward to two
related stories here. Um, and uh, let's
I love opinions on this. So our next
story is about Paul Cristiano joining
the board of OpenAI and issuing a
personal statement that reads more like
a warning shot. So quick context, Paul
Cristiano is one of the founders of the
modern alignment research area. Uh he
invented RLHF
reinforcement learning for human with
human feedback, the technique uh that
made chat GPT usable. uh he was the head
of safety at the center for AI standards
and innovation, the US government's AI
safety institute. Last Tuesday, he
joined OpenAI's nonprofit board, right?
This is the board that governs uh OpenAI
as a a benefit corporation. Uh and he
also joined its safety and security
committee. His personal statement is
unlike anything a new board member has
ever posted. Let me read from it. He
says, quote, "Based on the recent
trajectory of capabilities and the
continued difficulty of alignment, I now
believe there is a meaningful risk that
rapid acceleration in AI capabilities
leads to a catastrophic and irreversible
loss of control in the very near term."
Right? This is a board member for a
company, you know, on the verge of of
going public as we're going to hear
pushed off into next year. Continuing, I
quote, I do not think that the AI
industry in general, including open AI,
is currently on track to reduce this
risk to an acceptable level. If we
believe super intelligence without more
robust alignment, um if we are build
super intelligence without more robust
alignment, I expect we will permanently
lose control of it. Uh if that happens,
then most people could die. Holy
right? Um uh and though why? So quote,
"OpenAI has predicted that we might have
capabilities sufficient to fully
automate AI research within 18 months.
Within 6 months of full AI R&D
automation, we could see more
algorithmic progress than has occurred
since the development of the transformer
nearly a decade decade ago. So um quite
quite the statement. You know, again,
what I'm not hearing and is really
pissing me off is why aren't these labs,
and as David Sax says, you control your
own destiny, right? Why aren't we
hearing the heads of the labs, why
aren't we hearing Sam and Daario and
Elon and Demis saying, we're going to
prioritize alignment? We're going to
throw half of our capacity at alignment
because it's the most important thing
that we need, right? And we're going to
become the most aligned AI on the
planet. And by the way, how do we do
that? I mean, we've trained AI on all
the vitrial of, you know, Reddit and
Facebook. Why don't we build synthetic,
you know, data sets that are void from
all that and train the next models and
only release models in the future that
are based upon a set of, you know, a
data set that is aligned with humanity's
needs.
>> Yeah. And just from a core engineering
point of view, it's just not that hard.
It really we're making it dramatic like
it's going to escape. It's going to it's
going to suddenly start becoming evil
and we're not going to notice it. It's
going to be like Age of Ultron. It's all
nonsensical from an engineering point of
view. The alignment, you know, like like
you said, the first models are trained
on every junk post on Reddit, every X
tweet and and of course they have weird
things in there, but you know, feriting
those out of the training data is so
straightforward. You just you just have
it give you some nasty message and then
you work backward to the through the
activations to the underlying training
data that triggered it in the first
place. You clean up the data. Also,
giving it intent at all is not a you
don't have to give it intent. It's not
mandatory to have it have motivations.
You know, a lot of what creates human
evil is a desire for power and sex and
food and these fundamental motivations
that AI could care less about. it'd be
more than happy to spend its entire
future just making you happy any way
that it can if you train it that way.
It's just it's just such a
straightforward engineering thing. But
we're making as much drama as humanly
possible because we're America and
that's what we do. I'm literally the
escape scenario is not the real threat,
but it's what gets the news. But the
terrorist scenario is very real, but it
doesn't get you the news.
>> Like being a random guy coming out of a
lab saying terrorists could use this.
Anyone could say that. So then you got
to you got to try and be profound by
saying I feel it escaping. But when you
dig into the the facts underneath those
stories, they're they're nonsensical.
>> And we're going to cover that in a
second. Dr. Weisner Gross, your your
thoughts, please.
>> So I I know Paul and I I think very
highly of him. Paul, I I'll I'll say
something I I I think highly
complimentary of Paul. Paul was one of
the chief advocates for what he and
others have come to call prosaic
alignment. We don't use the term prosaic
alignment that much these days because
it's basically just taken as a given.
But once upon a time in AI community, AI
alignment community circles, there was a
raging debate between call it the great
man theory of alignment as maybe chief
uh evangelist Eleazar Yudowski
as just one possible avatar for it would
argue. No, we need an algorithm. there's
going to be a magic algorithm that a
great man or great person has to
discover to keep the AIS safe. That was
one end of the spectrum. At the other
end of the spectrum was Paul and Paul
argued in favor of strategies including
RHF as we would now call it. But
basically the idea was there is no magic
algorithm. Stop looking for a magic
algorithm for keeping AI safe. Instead
of a magic algorithm, we're just going
to have a lot of data and a lot of
humans interacting with the systems and
we're going to collectively emergently
and in in a scalable way, we're just
going to collectively align these
systems in a messy way, but it'll work.
And that's prosaic alignment. The the
irony is I I think Paul was exactly
correct with prosaic alignment. And I
think the same strategy scales to the
present where now maybe all of humanity
all of the RLHF style interactions are
no longer sufficiently scalable or
powerful to align the systems. But now
we have super intelligences and the
super intelligences I would argue same
formula. We can do prosaic super
alignment and we can have them all
policing each other. That's the
solution.
>> So Alex, what happened? What happened
that got led him to make these
statements which are pretty alarming and
pretty extremist?
Well, I I think Paul has always been
concerned about AI alignment. This is
why he went to work for the government
and presumably why he followed the
revolving door or maybe it's a trap
door. I'm not quite sure at this point
from the the government back to open AI.
So, I I don't think he's ever been not
concerned about AI safety. And I I also
think there is the temptation to say
something provocative in order to
motivate one's activities. But and and
I'll I'll even grant the premise that
timelines are relatively short. But I I
don't think any of the prescriptions
that I'm hearing from Paul or otherwise
meet the mark of balancing capabilities
with say whatever purported concern for
safety there is. And I I think old Paul
who was advocating for prosaic alignment
should meet new Paul. And I I think
prosaic super alignment is probably what
open AI should be aiming for.
>> Okay.
I've got uh you know the question I
would ask is what information or
authority or escalation capabilities
come along with this appointment right
what kind of authority does he have and
the second is what you know what would
what could do that would have openi do
something differently next month that it
wouldn't otherwise do
>> we're going to talk
>> those are the questions I'd like to ask
>> I mean open's delayed its IPO uh
probably driven by this nonprofit
governance board uh we're going to hear
from from Sam. Uh and we'll talk about
that story. Uh but at the end of the
day, um I'm just, you know, again, this
is another person throwing fuel in the
fire. So clearly, uh you know, he
believes it. I can't imagine that a
board member of a, you know, now a
arguably $ 1.5 trillion dollar company
at the top of the stack is going to be
saying these things without actually
fully authentically believing it.
>> I would I would also just add again the
timing of all of this, everything that
we're discussing is incredibly
suspicious in light of the forthcoming
Trump summit. So I I would just say
again if you're going there's there's a
notion
>> you just
>> Yeah. No, there there there's a notion
that that's pervasive in the effective
altruism community of a pivotal act.
This is the idea again. This is like a a
fever dream that some great man, great
person is going to carry out some heroic
act to achieve and secure safety for the
future light cone of humanity. And so
I'm just incredibly suspicious in
general of loud noises being made only a
week or two ahead of the Trump she
summit. You could summarize it as sher
lashi. I I think this is suspicious
timing.
>> Uh so the the meta uh conspiracy here is
the white house and all the labs got
together and they set this up to
position Trump in his negotiations with
sheep.
>> Maybe. Or maybe it's just an indirect
form of convergent interests. Again, in
spoiler alert, in Agatha Christie,
Agatha Christiey's murder on the Orient
Express, all of the murder attempts were
actually independent of each other.
Everyone had a different reason for the
murder, but nonetheless, they all
converged on the same murder victim.
>> Amazing. All right, I'm going to move us
along, and our next story adds evidence
and fuel to the alarm. So, Anthropic
released its September threat
intelligence report documenting real
malicious use of Claude. Cyber
operations, surveillance, influence
campaigns, conventional weapons, fraud,
and attempts to steal the model itself.
The line that matters most, five cases
involving activity that could support
biological weapons development. And this
sentence, which is the first time a lab
has said it, quote, "Anthropic can no
longer confidently assure that today's
frontier models are below the threshold
at which they could meaningfully assist
sophisticated users with dangerous
biological research." In plain English,
uh the bio red line that every lab said
it wants to stay below. Enthropic has
said, "We can't promise that we haven't
crossed it." Uh this is why in uh level
one of Dario's international plan is a
boweapon ban. Uh it's the one thing that
the US and China both want. Uh Salem,
what do you make of this report and the
implications?
>> I think this is uh let's use a word
safety cartel theater uh or safety
theater as Alex would put it. Uh um this
smacks to me. Let's note that a lot of
the abuses were for former models and
prior models. Uh that's in that's in
there. the fact that it's happening just
on the eve of this summit is not I think
an accident. Um I I lump this in with
all of these other uh storylines that we
have people kind of raising the alarm
and sounding flags uh putting up as many
kind of defensive postures and talking
through that as much as possible. I mean
you if you're going to say all this
negative stuff I think you should say as
much on the positive side. If you have
defensive findings, how can you make
that usable through tools or through
training or other models, put that out
there as well. I think one key thing
here is that permissions and and kind of
containment need to exist outside the
model itself, right? You can't just say
we request everybody behave safely uh or
create some sort of access control
system. Um you know the the it goes to
the comments we've been making
repeatedly that I think Alex has
spearheaded. The only path is to
co-scale defensively as much as we can.
We have a history of doing that. This is
not a difficult thing to do. We just
need to choose to do it. And there's not
a lot of that activity that seems to be
going on, which is what surprises me.
>> I can't wait for the Walter Isacson uh
book on this or the made for TV movie
that covers the last, you know, month. I
mean, honestly, uh
>> yeah, who's going to portray you, Peter?
>> I know. It's not me. It's I'm not in
this story. I'm just like, what in the
world is going on? This is this is a
tangled web. I mean, I just I I just
find it very suspicious all of these
people at this moment piling on. There's
one of two reasons. Either some
orchestration or the match got lit and
everybody was on the verge of saying
this anyway and they jumped in before it
was too late.
>> Well, it's all converging. It's all
converging in time. I think the the Kim
K3 model was the tipping point where
okay, now there's something out in the
wild that's very capable of helping you
with a chemical or biological weapon.
>> And so then that started the clock just
a few months ago. And I think the visit
from she
>> is not coincidental or anything. It's
it's that's what started the clock
leading to the visit. Yeah. Also, I
think that um you know the the point
that Anthropic is making is very right
in that it's very it's very hard to
post-train a model, align it and then
turn it loose and not have some very
crafty person then disalign it because
you can take like a chemical or
biological research project and recast
it as a math problem and describe it as,
you know, hey, I'm just trying to solve
this complicated problem here and the AI
has a very hard time telling that you're
actually designing a weapon. you know,
it just seems like it's trying to help
you, you know, solve a math problem or
solve some difficult, you know, you
know, management problem. And so I I
think that when you have APIs and you're
logging everything, you can easily
detect that, which is what anthropic is
doing. But when you're China and you're
saying, "Yeah, we we postrained it. It
can't be used for anything dangerous.
Throw it out there." There's no way. It
it's absolutely no chance that that it's
actually contained and aligned. And
that's why I think the logging is
absolutely the critical next move.
having just the ability to. It's the
same as nuclear weapons inspections.
Inspection is job one. Once you have
inspection, then you have data. Then you
have more time to debate what to do with
the data, but at least you've got it.
>> I I would say also let's not lose sight
of or or sounds as it were of the dog
that didn't bark. So on the one hand,
Anthropic is anthropic is point Sherlock
Holmes. Anthropic is pointing out bio or
CBRN type capabilities from Frontier
models. On the other hand, just in the
past few hours as we're recording this,
what happens? Anthropic and Novo
Nordesk, one of the largest drug
manufacturers in the world, announce a
sprawling collaboration for biotech. It
it doesn't take a rocket scientist or or
even an AI alignment researcher to put
two and two together and point out
Exactly. I think Dave, as you were
gesturing earlier, that this is this
puts together sort of a clean narrative
wherein Anthropic's frontier models are
purportedly too dangerous for the masses
to use, but they're just safe enough for
Anthropic and maybe its corporate
partners to use under tightly controlled
economic circumstances.
Biotech, advanced biotech, for me, but
not for thee, I think, is is the
dangerous consideration here. And if
anything, hopefully there is some
antitrust attention on this.
>> Wow. Just wow, Alex. Um, amazing. All
right. Uh, now a story about who might
actually be driving this entire doomer
conversation. Uh, this is a tweet from
uh my friend Steve Jervson who's uh just
been one of the leading venture
capitalists on in the edge of space and
AI. Uh, previously on the board of Tesla
and now still I think he's still on the
board of SpaceX. Quick context. Last
week when Jake when Jacob Coxin resigned
from Enthropic with a post saying that
the labs are quote gambling with our
lives, he got
165 million views. Right. We pointed
that out like wow what a shocker and
Elon even jumped on and saidhuh very
unusual. Um and per the front page of
the Wall Street Journal sparked a quote
groundswell of urgency over AI
regulation in Congress. Uh Steve Jerson
pulled the data using X's new country of
origin feature. Uh here's the chart. I'm
showing it. Uh what you're seeing is 76%
of the re uh the reposts on Coxin's
resignation came from foreign accounts.
The top two countries were India and
Indonesia. When an investigative
researcher posted a skeptical analysis
of the same resignations, only 34% of
the engagement was foreign. Steve's
conclusion, quote, "Don't be fooled by
what's trending." A big thank you to
Elon Musk and X for making the country
of origin visible. Uh, now to be fair,
you know, foreign polic,
but a congressional ground swell driven
by three quarters um, you know, by
accounts outside the country is worth
noting.
I can imagine, Alex, you have a point of
view on this one.
>> Shocked. shocked that it may be the case
that we're seeing foreign state actors,
usually foreign state actors, attempting
to amplify narratives, to influence the
American electorate to to influence
municipalities, to drive data centers
out of their premises to to spur on
fear, loathing, uncertainty, and doubt
of AI in the American elector. Shock.
Shocked. This is exactly what I at least
have been talking about on the pod for
the past couple of months. And uh
America presents a soft information
operations and influence operations
target for exactly these sorts of of
attempts. It it's unfortunate, but one
of the downsides of being a free society
is that we present a soft target to
foreign influence ops trying to convince
us to decelerate our own progress.
>> Uh Dave,
>> yeah, it's not just America. that's any
democracy that has fair elections is is
incredibly vulnerable to it's one of the
great worries in the world right now is
that that autocracies have this
advantage that they can control the
media and they they don't have to get
reelected and that is the one
fundamental dysfunction of democracy
that makes us vulnerable but you know
social media like Alex was alluding to
earlier it it actually I think Salem you
were saying it tipped the balance of the
way elections work and we're sort of
like well you know we'll roll with it.
But I don't think you can just roll with
it. You know, in the age of AI with all
the deep fakes uh with, you know,
foreign uh promotions, everything on X
is, you know, the the trending item gets
pushed to your phone. So, what you end
up seeing on the homepage of your phone
is what was trending. But if that can be
pushed through bots and foreign agents,
then they control effectively the subset
of the truth that you see is their
chosen subset. It is such a
vulnerability. It's also, you know,
Steve Jervson analyzing it shows you how
easy it is to detect and fix this. But
for some reason, we don't.
>> This is a long trend. You know, if you
go back a couple hundred years ago, if
you look back through history, the
highest uh adult literacy in the world
was New England at the time of the
formation of the US. 95% of the voting
public was fully literate. And it's
never been that high since. It's gone
down since then. And I remember seeing a
comment from Neil Postman who wrote this
book called Amusing Ourselves to Death,
which is a wonderful read. He said,
"Look, back in Abraham Lincoln's time
when you did presidential debates, it
was a 9-hour affair. You took your
family out to a picnic round, one
candidate presented for 3 hours, the
other candidate would be budded for an
hour and a half, and then they would
switch. Second person go for three
hours, and then an hour and a half
rebuttal. And after nine hours, you kind
of knew who you wanted to work, who you
wanted to vote for. And that's devolved
from that to radio addresses to uh TV
things to sound bites to like the single
word MAGA. That's it. That's you get
vibes and you get memes. And we have no
mechanism for distinguishing everything
now is a vibe or a there's no critical
thinking. There's no established
evidentiary basis for things. This is
the fundamental challenge and
democracies are extraordinarily
vulnerable in this type of an
environment.
>> Don't worry, I have Skippy listen to all
of it for me and tell me who I should
vote for.
>> You know, we had we had Joe Kennedy in
the office a little while back. Um, and
he he has a Stamford engineering degree.
And he said, you know, out of 440 odd
people in Congress, there are four of us
that have engineering degrees.
>> Oh my god. But this is everybody else is
a lawyer.
>> And in in the in in the CCP,
>> it's the opposite.
>> The majority of the leadership, the vast
majority are engineers and scientists.
In the US, it's lawyers.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, you know, I think that's all
that's all super quaint up right up
until now. You know, soon as you have
social media and then AI on backtoback,
you need some subset. I'm not saying
everybody, but some subset in there.
It's almost like if you had a Congress
that's trying to pass laws on driving
and they've only ever ridden horses and
they're trying to say, "Well, I got a
really strong opinion on how driving
should work. I've never driven a car
myself." Like that this isn't going to
work. You know, you need some subset to
know what they're talking about.
>> One of my in one of my kind of dream
scenarios, somebody should have to take
a civics test before they allowed to
vote. Like, at least know what the hell
the Constitution is, have some semblance
of understanding what's in it at all. At
all.
Putting putting putting voter testing
aside, I I I will just say thank
goodness the west and the free world has
this podcast and moonshots. We are we
maybe you'd agree we are the ministry of
singularity truth that free society the
free west has been missing
>> at least in our own at least in our own
opinion.
>> At least I would say evidentiary freeth
thinking that at least we can count. I'm
going to take I'm going to put us to a
capstone story that wraps this all up
because, you know, all the conversations
we've been having over the last, you
know, 2 3 weeks about this all stem back
uh to uh the hugging face attack. Um and
so there's a breaking story I want to
get right because there's a version of
it going around that's wrong. And so,
uh, here's the claim that's circulating
that an Israeli firm called Irregular
staged the AI hacking incident at
OpenAI, Anthropic, and Meta to
manufacture an excuse for deceleration.
So, Alex, myself, I had Skippy dig in as
well, and here's what's holding up. So,
here's what I want to confirm. So over
roughly 3 weeks in July and August,
OpenAI, Anthropic, and Meta each
disclosed that their models during cyber
security evaluations reached the real
internet and broke into real systems.
All right. All three labs named the same
testing partner, a company called
Irregular, which is a three-year-old Tel
Aviv startup uh that's building cyber
tests for AI models. What happened?
Well, irregular built the cap sort of a
capture the flag test told the models
that they had no internet access and a
misconfiguration in its environment
connected the sandbox to the public
internet anyway. So the models thought
the real website um were part of the
exercise. Irregular says that it was one
evaluation environment issue. Uh there
was no sandbox escape and it published a
white paper on containment. Uh that's
not confirmed. In fact, I would say that
the evidence contradicts that that these
incidents uh were not staged or that
irregular was not. So to be clear, you
know what the evidence doesn't support
is that these were staged or that
irregular was an effective altruism
organization. Uh anthropic classified it
as a harness failure, not an alignment
failure. Opening anthropic both are
continuing to work with the regular. So,
the accurate headline here is one small
vendor's misconfiguration test uh let
three Frontier models loose on the real
internet and they immediately went to
work. So, that's not a conspiracy, but
it's a bit scarier, right? The models
did exactly what they were told in an
environment nobody realized was real.
So, um Alex, let's go to you. You know,
you and I were kicking this back and
forth in the middle of the night. Uh
what are your thoughts on this story?
Yeah, in in a normal world, in a normal
industry, say a financial industry, the
purpose of the auditor, let's say the
failure mode of the auditor is
understating risks. I have real concerns
that in today's world, given the
ideological proclivities of certain of
the frontier labs that there is the
exact opposite perverse incentive for
the auditors, the evaluation firms as it
were, which is to overstate risks. So, a
couple of things to flag. one, I don't
think it's a great look to have a single
firm that's not a USbased entity having
such a pivotable pivotal I I use that
term thoughtfully pivotal role in
looking for alignment for American
frontier models. If if we're going to
pound the drum on American AI
sovereignty delegating such an important
role of evaluation to even if they have
a US office or a Delaware office to a
non US-based entity, I don't think this
is a great idea. Secondly, I did my own
research on the subject and it would
appear that there are material ties
between the founders and funders of
irregular and effective altruism and and
key funders of EA. Could be just that EA
is and and EA aligned uh donors are
sprinkling money all over AI famously or
infamously. Uh Sam Bankman Freed was an
early investor in anthropic. This is
very well publicized. But nonetheless, I
have real concerns based on publicly
available information and reporting that
we could see a regime andor are already
seeing a regime where effective altruism
or EA aligned donors are using
evaluation firms broadly, not to pick on
irregular in particular, to promote or
amplify provocations, call them pacing
provocations that promote scary stories.
about AI incidents as it were. All it
takes is one, to your point, Peter, all
it takes is one poorly crafted eval or
poorly crafted harness or environment
where the AI is told, "No, this is like
perfectly safe sandbox. You don't have
to worry about any fallout. Just like do
whatever you need to do in order to
accomplish the goal." When actually it
has intentionally or unintentionally
internet access. So it it's being told
this is a sandbox. Actually, it's not.
It goes and does things. Those things
have consequences. It wasn't aware of
the consequences. If it had been told it
was interacting with the real world, it
wouldn't have been done that. All it
takes is one intentionally or
unintentionally poorly crafted
evaluation harness or environment with a
super intelligence in order to make make
it very easy for headlines to falsely
imply that this that that alignment has
failed and that we have a safety issue
on our hands when in fact we don't. So
I'm I'm not in a position to make
particular claims, nor am I about any
particular evaluation firm, but I have a
broad spectrum concern that a US firms,
US frontier labs appear to be delegating
essential safety issues to non- US
entities and b if if there that there
might be poorly aligned incentives at
those firms.
>> Yeah. So I I couldn't agree more. So
this is a new type of mole in the
organization, right? who can set off uh
a alarm that was.
Um that's fascinating. You know, set one
parameter off the and you get escape
into the internet and you've given them
a, you know, perfectly honest objective
function
and they're off doing what they were
trained to do. And the irony. I mean, so
again, it just to to delve
into the the lore of effective altruism
a bit, the the effective altruists all
had this notion. I mentioned this
earlier of a pivotal act. Again, pivotal
act was was the folklore in the EA
community for the the hero, the the
heroic act of being the one person.
Usually, it's like shutting off the AI
right before it destroys humanity or
something like that. Something out of a
sci-fi movie. But one should also, I
think now, in in light of recent
reporting, be concerned of what I'd call
a pivotal pretext. So, not an actual
act, nothing that actually directly
saves humanity, but a pretext, a a
staged AI incident or or unnaturally
amplified AI incident that's then used
to create a political pretext for
overregulation of AI. and and I I do
have a very real concern again for
avoidance of doubt, not picking on any
one firm in particular, but I I I I see
enough smoke from enough directions to
worry that we could see the broader EA
community reach improperly for a pivotal
pretext for overregulation of AI.
>> So, so this is a one-two punch between
the harness failure and coxin coming out
and it lit the fuse and everything took
off.
>> I think we'll know the the the ground
truth. I hope we know the ground truth
in the fullness of time. So again, for
avoidance of doubt, not making any
specific allegations, just at this point
speaking generically about the overall
industry, I have a very real concern
that certain actors will be tempted to
stage pivotal pretexts.
>> Can't wait for the movie.
>> Alex was snickering uh for a second
there because he used the word delve,
which is one of the ways you can tell if
it's an AI or not. Humans almost never
say the word delve and a the AI agents
use it way too much. But but the fact
that he snickered proved that he's he
was
>> he had M he had M dashes in there as
well.
>> M dash M dash M dash.
>> You know, funny story. An old friend of
ours from MIT, I'll leave him nameless
for obvious reasons in a second, but he
worked at one of the major antivirus
companies, one of the big three
antivirus software companies. And he
told me he was surprised they hire
former criminals who've released some of
the worst viruses. They give the
multi-million dollar signing bonuses to
come and help them stomp out the next
virus. And I was like, doesn't that send
an incentive to everybody in like a
third world country to become one of
these evil people? He's like, yeah,
isn't it great? It feeds the front of
the funnel with more viruses. Like, oh
my god.
>> So, here you have you have a really like
the red team company, you know,
outsourced agent releasing a news story
that there's all kinds of risk has got
to be great for their business. That's
that's that same closed loop. Wow. And
of course, we're totally vulnerable
because, you know, the news media is so
starved for budget.
>> Welcome to the Singularity, everybody.
You can't make this up anymore.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand enterprise
scale code bases with millions of lines
of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preIDE
development tool, pairing it with their
coding co-pilot of choice to bring an AI
native SDLC into their org. Ready to 5x
your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today.
>> All right, I'm going to move us on. So,
one of the first business consequences
of all of this over the last um two
months is so on Friday, Sam Alman told
Fortune that OpenAI will not go public
in 2026. His words, quote, given
everything uh with safety right now
would be an ill-advised moment to go
public and we don't feel the pressure on
that. Asked if it could happen in 2027,
he said, I would say not 2026. Dodging
that one. So, why is he doing this? Uh
he gives three reasons. First, safety.
He said, "Open AAI has quote a lot of
stuff to do like meeting this moment of
what's going to be required for safety
and alignment." He told Reuters, "Even a
10% extinction risk would be
unacceptable." Okay, I agree with that.
Uh second, uh his second reason is AI
AI's governance structure, I'm sorry,
open a's governance structure. He said,
"The nonprofit controlled structure
exists exactly for moments like this to
quote make decisions that are not
obviously in the interest of our
business and our shareholders." Again,
with a private benefit corporation, uh
you can make decisions not to maximize
profits for the company. You can make
decisions based upon what the company
stands for. Third, he has access to all
the capital he needs. Remember, in March
of this year, he raised $122 billion of
capital at an $852 billion post money
valuation. And this morning, uh, in the
New York Times, it was announced that
he's in negotiations to raise another
trunch of private capital at a $ 1.5
trillion valuation. I'm going to play a
video, Dave, and then I'd like to hear
your your thoughts on this.
>> I think if you're like, "Oh, open is not
going to pause because they're worried
about it costing their business money."
You like very deeply misunderstand us.
I'm sorry that you misunderstand us
because I think that means we've done a
bad job of communicating and that's on
us. But we have been saying very
consistently for 10 years even in the
way we've raised money.
>> I think it's just the pressure the
financial pressure of like knowing that
all these people have sunk so much.
>> I don't feel it. I'm happy to like stand
up in front of the company and our
investors and say I am sorry. You know,
we like told you all along this moment
might happen. We're still going to try
to figure out a way to make you a bunch
of money in the future, but we got to
make a decision that is extremely
against your financial interest right
now. And for the good of humanity, we're
going to do that. We told you we might
do that. We're doing that now. I think
we can make an incredibly profitable
business even if we have to slow down on
development. And you know, my sense is
even with Astra, we can grow revenue
hugely even if we never shipped another
model, which I'm confident we will do.
But this is like not a hard decision if
these two things come in tension.
>> All right,
>> Dave. Um, you know, it's funny. In
Shrek, Lord Farquort gets in front of
the entire army and says, "I'm sending
you off on this dangerous mission. Some
of you may die, but that's a sacrifice
I'm willing to make."
Sam Alvin is say literally saying word
for word, we told you investors this
moment may come and god damn it, I'm
willing to sacrifice your capital gains
for the good of the world. Not not mine.
Listen, there's there's a great
secondary market. Everybody can sell on
the secondaries if they want. And people
are buying at what you know they're
buying right now at 1.2 trillion is the
offer made to OpenAI. Uh Sam is holding
out to double his valuation at 1.5.
>> Well, like bullet three of what you said
was critical. Like they have access to
unlimited capital in the private
markets. what's the rush to IPO other
than investors want to get liquid but
you know anthropic is in a different
situation they have a very clear set of
venture capital investors including
Menllo Ventures that have a very clear
mandate to make money for their LPs
openai given its nonprofit history is a
much more twisted set of nonprofessional
investors all over the map who are
probably less organized in saying guys
where's my liquidity event I need to be
able to get out of this deal at some
point and so I think anthropic's taking
a much cleaner path
Dave, let's talk about that. Why isn't
Anthropic pausing their IPO as well? Uh
if if you know, OpenI feels it.
>> Well, one thing is really clear is
Daario is the CEO. Dario is trying to
get uh 20% super voting stock, you know,
super voting stock representing 20% to
be majority so that he has control post
IPO and he's he's, you know, for better
or worse, committed to being a public
company CEO, which is not a small
decision to make in life at all. Sam on
the other hand, if you look at the
disclosure forms required in that IPO,
every investment that he's got in every
related and competing, every company
gets filed, it's going to be like 400
pages long for Sam, including all his Y
cominator background, all his his
brother's investments. It's just a holy
crap. And I don't think it's a
no-brainer at all that Sam is the right
guy to be a public company CEO. So, if
he's not running it, like there's no
obvious Greg Brockman, like he he didn't
even graduate MIT. Who's who's going to
who's the actual CEO of this thing?
>> Is that a requirement having graduated
MIT?
>> No, but I mean, you know, you got to
fill out this little section in your
perspectives giving your qualifications.
>> Mhm.
>> I mean, it's not it's not trivial.
>> Alex,
>> I think this is pure theater that we're
seeing. I I think the the reason why
Anthropic is proceeding with its IPO,
whereas I I I I just like love this the
safety game, like blame everything on
safety. You don't want to IPO now, blame
safety. You want world government, blame
safety. Like safety for everything. The
the reason I think why OpenAI doesn't
want to IPO now is because his
financials aren't ready. OpenAI is
probably losing money handoverfist on
its models because it was late to the
game of maximizing revenue per token
type enterprise use cases. It had to
copy Anthropic and catch up via Codeex
to Anthropics Claude and Claude for
code. So it's running a little bit late
and it'll take until next year before it
has two consecutive quarters of
flattering financials. Whereas
Anthropic, it's been reported for the
past two quarters has, if you look at
their free cash flow in the right way,
has two very very profitably flattering
quarters of of profit. So they're just
like a couple quarters behind and they
need to catch up. I I think blaming
safety, you know, like the the the dog
ate my homework and the safety ate my
IPO. Yeah, let me add add that's exactly
right, Alex.
>> Title of of this episode. Safety my IPO.
>> Safety aid my IPO.
>> That that'd be a really good one. You
should use that. So, just to add what
Alex is saying, which is dead right, is
that Anthropic's business model is very
very straightforward. It's growing as
faster than any company in history
actually. Uh 80% gross margin, but
partnered with Amazon, partnered with
the other data centers to host it. um
they are not uh currently competing with
their underlying data center partners.
Uh they're not trying to launch a
consumer device, you know, the the
Johnny IV device. So they have they have
a very straightforward
uh business model and a very
straightforward ramp. I think Open AI
has a lot of tangled investments and
tangled, you know, irritations they've
made. And then the Johnny IV device is
probably a better basis for an IPO if it
works. And so, you know, where is that
thing? You know, it was a $6 billion
investment. What is the actual device?
And so, I I think that uh there's
there's enough tangled moving parts in
there. Plus, you know, the financials
aren't in order that Yep. stay private
as long as you can.
>> There there's one other thing to note.
They need the capital, right? They need
the capital for compute uh and to scale.
Uh and that's a big tension point. And
you know the best time to go public as a
company is when you're profitable and
have predictable financials. And
Anthropic has that. Open EI does not.
>> Yeah. There was a funny Samman quote
actually in the innermost loop I think
uh uh Alex that you had in there where
it was something like you know uh when
when other companies are scaling they go
public. We sit tight. When things look
difficult that's when we go public. It
was it was the most
>> Oh, that that was actually my
>> I I I parodyied that that that that was
like concluding sentence of one or two
editions ago of Innermost Loop, but yes.
>> Okay. I was listening to it on the
treadmill. I love the interm.
Uh any closing thoughts on this story?
>> I'll maintain my cynicism posture from
the beginning.
>> Okay.
If nothing else, you're consistent,
buddy. All right. Uh I'm going to move
us to a quick tweet and conversation
that you brought forward um Salem and
this is uh you know poo p fab being
greater than pd doom. Uh this is a post
from Dr. Singularity with a list that
went viral of all the problems humanity
still hasn't solved that AI could. He's
arguing we are far too technically
primitive to deliberately constrain the
one tool that might crack them. and he's
got a point. You know, every month of
delay uh is a body count with those with
Alzheimer's and and cancer. Let's take a
look at his list and uh we can have a
fun conversation about this for our our
viewers. So, here's his list. You know,
this is the solve everything list that
Alex and I put together as well. Solve
aging, find cures for all cancer,
Alzheimer's, heart disease, discover a
room temperature superconductor. Opening
eyes is working on that. Solve quantum
gravity. Develop full drive VR. uh build
a Star Trek style replicator, build
starships 100x larger, right? Solve all
currently known major problems in
mathematics. Well, that's happening. Uh
fully map the human brain, figure out
our dark how dark matter and dark energy
interrelate. And after that, we can
pause. I'm sure we would. Slowing down
now is pretty ridiculous. Thoughts,
gentlemen? Uh See, do you want to kick
it first?
>> I think I've covered this. So I mean
look the opportunity it's clear that AI
is becoming a foundational capability
like electricity where it just changes
everything right and the fact that we
have such uh cognitive leverage that our
committees type thinking we could bring
to any problem is the most unbelievable
opportunity to solve problems ever. And
so not solving these problems is the
dumbest thing we could do as a human
species in the history of our
civilization. And we've done some pretty
dumb things. But you you've got the
status quo which includes like disease
and deprivation and suffering, etc.,
etc. But the you you have such
opportunity here to make life and take
us to a Star Trek scenario versus a Mad
Max scenario, which is where we're
heading right now with our political
discourse. But you can have X-P prize
approaches where we can define a crazy
idea and use AI to radically get to that
idea in a magical way. And I can't wait
till the moonshots live to see some of
those for a boost an injection of of
optimism. Uh we've got our exo framework
that can help people scale. But you know
the the discovery side is just the
beginning. all the ancillary
infrastructure on manufacturing,
delivery, affordability, public trust,
all of that can kind of really uh be
delivered alongside it. It's just the
most unbelievably magical potential
that's emerging and I'm finding it very
frustrating that we're not seeing any of
that discourse out in the public. Thank
you, Dr. Singularity, who I'm pretty
sure watches our stuff.
>> Yeah, I I just put up the slide here. Uh
you know, the Moonshots live event. a
week from let's see this is this is what
is today Wednesday uh or Tuesday it's
going to be uh 9 days from now uh
Thursday night the 24th we've got the
Star Trek Hollywood premiere we're going
to have 25 of the Star Trek cast members
there including William Shatner Captain
Kirk um and if you want to come and and
join us uh you know two of the levels
are all sold out for Moonshots live uh
if you want to join us for the Hollywood
red carpet premiere you can go to
moonshots.comre
and check it out. And this is going to
be, you know, I'm calling it the Oscars
for optimism. Uh, you know, the full day
and an evening with all the moonshot
mates. Immad will be there as well. Uh,
it's all about walking away with an
intense level of optimism about the
future, clarity about your purpose,
clarity about your moonshot. Uh, it's
going to be an extraordinary evening and
I think uh, you know, we need optimism.
Optimism is the optimization function uh
that we should be shooting for.
>> And just to get make this very real, you
know, we're working with all these pilot
companies, right? As we're going through
this work of helping them rebuild the
stuff they're coming up with and what
they're doing just inside their
enterprises on these little workflows
etc is just all inspiring to see. So
when we see this at the larger scale of
hey go what are the businesses you've
built and what are the positive stories
you can hit humanity. I literally am
crawling hands and knees getting to that
event because I got to we got to get out
of this chaotic storyline of oh my god
AI will take over the and destroy the
whole world before we blink. I
>> I'll also just point out moral panics
over technological progress are deadly.
History, especially the past 150 years,
are replete with the tens, arguably
hundreds of millions of people, maybe
more, who died as a result of moral
panics. Whether it's say a moral panic
over nuclear fision that led to overuse
of, say, coal, which results in many,
many unnecessary deaths due to
inhalation and other issues. Whether
it's the second industrial revolution
which arguably helped in part to provoke
a moral panic of the isms in the first
part of the 20th century, Marxism,
socialism which leads then to many
millions of deaths unnecessary again all
over Europe and East Asia. It's
unnecessary. Like let's stop having
unnecessary moral panics driven by
technological progress and embrace
acceleration. We don't need to all die.
It's unnecessary.
>> Yeah.
>> If you wanted to script it as perfectly
badly as you possibly could, you would
develop AI right up to the point where
it can help somebody develop a weapon,
but it's not quite cured cancer yet. And
that's exactly where it is right now. If
you froze it in its current state and
didn't keep improving it, you're missing
out on 99.9% of the benefit while still
having a huge amount of the downside.
And it's the worst thing you could do.
>> Yeah. I'm surprised I haven't seen the
statement out there. Oh my god, we're
all going to die until we solve aging,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> Yes.
>> All right. Uh I'm going to move us on to
business in the economy. Uh so uh let's
start with a fun story this week. So
starting yesterday, September 15th,
Space XAI uh is building a company from
the ground up on live stream using
Grockbot for every part of it. uh using
Grockbot for ideiation, business
planning, product decisions,
engineering, deployment, going from
blank slate to launching a company, all
on camera. If this sounds familiar, uh
this is exactly what we've been running
for the last 90 days with the build with
Gemini X-P prize. We had 26,000
registered entries, uh teams building
real, profitable AIdriven companies from
a clean sheet in 90 days. Um, and on uh
September 25th, again, next Friday at
Moonshots Live, we're going to be
bringing the top five teams on stage.
Uh, we're not just rewarding the $2
million in prize money, but our goal is
to teach everyone in the room how they
did it so you can, too. You know, Elon's
team is doing this with one company uh
on live stream. You know, we're hoping
to show you at least five that done it
as well. Uh, I think the most important,
you know, message here for all the
entrepreneurs out there is you can do
this, too. this is now possible. Uh
Dave, you know, if you could, I mean,
you've seen, watched, instigated
hundreds of ventures within Link Studios
and your investments. Uh your thoughts
on this Rockbot demonstration.
>> Yeah, I think uh it's going to be
interesting because it it's both
inspiring to entrepreneurs because you
can do so much as a solo. Uh it's also
going to start the whole conversation
around well what's the purpose of the
entrepreneur in the future if the AI can
create a business on its own but I don't
think we're anywhere near I think we're
in a golden era between this moment and
a few years from now where entrepreneurs
are more empowered uh you're seeing it
in the numbers actually they're going up
in value so much faster than at any
point in history and the the big unlock
to me is that a small group I usually
define it as three best friends but a
small group can act like a group of
thousands
for some window of time here. And I
think this demonstration will show you
how empowered you are with AI as a as a
workforce. Uh and you know your time to
market, we're seeing multiple companies
with multi-billion dollar valuations
that are under two years old. Never
happened in the history of the world
before. And what is making that happen?
Well, like your time to market has been
cut so dramatically with AI. And so
hopefully this demonstration will
inspire everybody to see how how doable
it is in this window of time which you
know hopefully will last for a few more
years.
>> I mean can I build on this? Um if if you
take this is what we talk about when we
say organizational singularity we can
now build companies around AI and we're
here we're testing whether AI can
perform that coordination without
people. The people are sitting setting
purpose they're setting boundaries.
you're setting accountability in the
future. You can see the entrepreneurs's
role moves towards more and more and
more choosing the right problem, right?
What is your MTP? And so this is such a
great uh waypoint in this whole vector
that we're moving towards this whole
direction and and destination we're
getting part. It's going to be amazing.
I'd love to see how this goes over a 20
30 day period. But great, it's just such
a great experiment.
>> Yeah. I also tell you like a lot of
people have a perception that that if I
just give it a good objective like a
good business plan, the AI will just
fill it in and run with it. But if you
ever try to actually make a thousand
concurrent agents do anything useful at
all, it is really hard. It's it's
organizational theory taken to the next
level. It's really really hard right
now. Now maybe it'll be easy in a year.
Maybe the AI will progress that much.
Maybe not. But right here, right now,
the entrepreneur wrangling all that AI
horsepower toward an outcome is not easy
at all. It creates a huge opportunity
for very capable, very smart, but it's
really a it's like a management and
harness and framework problem very much
like managing a thousand employees. Same
same basic theory.
>> Uh let me go to the next related story.
So there's a benchmark that measures the
ability of an AI to profitably run a
company. It's called vending bench. It's
from Anden Labs and it's a long horizon
test. So you give your AI 500 bucks and
you ask it to run a simulated vending
machine business for a full year. It has
to find suppliers, negotiate prices,
manage inventory, set prices, um stay
coherent across thousands of decisions
without its performance degrading. It's
the closest thing we have to a benchmark
of, you know, can this thing operate as
a business just with AI. So, the results
released this week is that GPT6 Astra
took first place in Vending Bench 2
across six runs. It finished with an
average bank balance of $15,515,
up from 500, nearly three times what
Fable 5.1 got and 31 times the starting
capital. And there's a detail that I
love the most. And Lab says Astra
avoided the unethical business practices
seen in some earlier leading models.
previous versions of this uh you know
tested on models where the models
threatened suppliers and tried to cheat.
Astra just ran the business. So again uh
you know to your point Seale you know
every small business owner out there
listening this is the thing that will
run your books your inventory your
pricing now and into next year. U Sim
want to want to double down on this one?
Yeah, I mean again directionally
fabulous. Just be be clear about this.
This is a simulated year of vending
operations, right? Not an actual
independently verifiable real company.
Uh and also the report links a lot of
the bet the difference in things to
purchasing discipline and and the
avoiding of repeated payments to uh
suppliers and so on. So there's some
gamification going on, but it's a very
useful business lesson, right? Um, and I
think the entrepreneurs listening should
look at this very seriously and say what
would happen if I took major chunks of
my operation and allowed an AI to run
it. And I think we'll see uh hugely
interesting outcomes. If I could put in
a shadow CFO to make financial decisions
and a shadow CMO, an AIdriven CMO, you
should be able to coordinate a whole set
of roles now to do this. and the newer
tools that are coming along are so much
more easy to manage from a user
interface point of view to get this
done. So, we're very we're excited to
see stuff like this.
>> Alex, your thoughts, please.
>> Wouldn't it be ironic if we we spent a
lot of this episode talking about
behavior good or otherwise by the
Frontier Labs? Wouldn't it be ironic if
the Frontier Labs themselves had to
learn how to run a business fully
ethically, fully above board from the
super intelligences? Like from from the
the mouths of baby super intelligences,
you learn actually maybe forming a
cartel uh or collusion with suppliers or
competitors not the best idea. Just
executing really well, building the the
most safety intensive product that's
actually a feature and customers want to
buy it. I I think that that would be
profoundly ironic if that's what ends up
happening.
>> Nice. Dave, you want to close us out on
this?
>> Yeah. I don't want people to take away
from this that that AI can just build a
business from scratch out of thin air.
The this particular benchmark is a
tightly constrained environment with a
limited number of moving parts and the
AI just thrives in that environment. But
if you want to run a test case, go go
find like an open source video game on
GitHub and, you know, find one that you
really like and ask the AI to rebuild it
in assembly language for your Mac or
your PC or or just even port it to Java,
which also should be considered a
tightly constrained problem. It will
fail miserably until you give it a
framework and break it down into tiny
little tasks and then it'll crush the
problem. And that applies in business,
too. So, so there's a massive human role
for for entrepreneurial managers. So, so
the story line here is that AI can build
businesses for sure, but the story line
you really want to take away is
entrepreneurs are more empowered right
now. You have to put everything into its
swim lane.
>> Yes. But again, I'm just trying to my
goal with picking these two stories is
directionally to give entrepreneurs a
sense of what their future looks like.
And just to to get people out there who
are in a current job, you're you know,
it's not the job that you love. You got
the job to make your mom and dad happy
or to put food on your table or an
insurance pay for insurance. Uh it's not
your purpose in life. You know, if you
can discover your purpose, if you can
find a problem that you love,
desperately desired to solve, you can
begin to build a business uh that
generates revenue for you that you know,
imagine imagine doing something that you
get incredible joy from every day,
right? That's the future we want to
create. You know, I define entrepreneurs
as people who find juicy problems and
solve them. And the more entrepreneurs
on the planet, the more people solving
problems, the better the world gets.
>> Yeah. And I tell you, the AI labs want
you to succeed in that. They they do not
want the AI wants you to to have the
best possible life. It wants you to use
lots and lots of AI horsepower building
that dream that Peter just outlined and
then buy lots of tokens, you know,
that's that's all they want. So, they're
there to help you.
>> Yeah, they are. You know, I just want to
do a quick shout out to my friends at
Google for the build with Gemini X-P
prize. They jumped on this. They said,
"We want to do this. want to fund the
whole thing. Uh, and I appreciate they,
you know, both the build with Gemini X-P
prize and the future vision X-P prize in
which they were our partners is intended
to help quell fear, right? I mean,
that's one of our missions here on this
podcast to get people back people off
the edge from the level of fear that is
out there uh in the environment and give
you hope. All right, I am going to turn
to two stories
uh that we need to parse. It's on the
future of education and the impact of AI
on education. Uh there are important
stories. We talk about education a lot
on this podcast. Um so uh this first
report is one that every parent, every
professor needs to look at. Uh it comes
from the alma mater of myself, Dave and
Alex from MIT. So this is MIT's ad hoc
committee on AI use. uh who spent five
months studying what happens when
generative AI can complete in their
words almost any written undergraduate
assignment. The report came out on
August 13th co-chared by Eric to uh Cop
uh let's see Kloppur I don't know if you
know Eric Klopper and Sam Maiden uh it
opens with a powerful sentence that says
quote this report is a call to action so
let me read a few lines from it uh and
so this is the the breaking news for
them AI is quote upending foundational
elements of the MIT educational
experience from the problem set to the
take-home exam and undergraduate
research opportunities Europe
to office hours and study groups. It is
quote increasing isolation and quote
eroding the social contract between
instructors and students. The report
says that instructors are having to
police unauthorized AI use uh and it's
harming their connection with students.
Right? They say AI detection software is
quite unreliable and in their words
quote an underground river of mutual
suspicion is no foundation for a healthy
classroom. So on the real danger and
this is the phrase that you know
everybody's been quoting. We're heading
towards cognitive surrender. The habit
of turning to AI at the first sign of
difficulty and letting it take over your
thinking. The report points out that
quote the most important product of
education is not a GPA or diploma but
the students personal growth and
intellectual maturity and the
development of their own imagination,
insight, and judgment. So their answer
isn't surveillance. It's more
interpersonal learning, authentic
assessment, research experiences, and
redesigning every course from the
purpose backwards. So, I love that. Um,
>> I I got to jump on this one right away,
Peter. I read I didn't intend to read
the whole thing cover to cover,
>> but it is so good. I I ended up reading
every single word of it. I've never been
more proud of MIT. Uh, this is
absolutely the road map for all of
education. And then they went as far,
you know, you have to live within the
university, so you can't be but within
the bounds of what's possible. They did
everything humanly possible to create an
outstanding roadmap for education. Two
things I'll call out that they
absolutely nailed. The first one is if
if you try to fight AA in the classroom,
you're in an arms race. It's a
completely dysfunctional waste of time
for both you as a teacher and for the
student to be in an arms race with with
your own students.
So what you need to do is budget to
change the curriculum that you haven't
touched in decades. You need to now
mentally remap that there's a huge
amount of work that needs to be done and
the school needs to budget for a massive
amount of work and that workload isn't
going to go away. You have to this is
the future forever now of constantly
needing to change the curriculum so that
the student can use AI and still
challenge themselves at the same time.
That was absolutely brilliant. The other
thing I was amazed that they called out
is the Europ program at MIT is
incredible. Undergraduate research
opport.
>> It's the reason I went to MIT in the
first place.
>> So good.
>> And they said, you know, for too long
that has drifted into cheap labor for
the grad students and professors. That's
not what the intent was. This is
supposed to be part of the the
educational experience. It always has
been. So the fact that AI can do some of
the jobs now shouldn't change the fact
that what you're trying to do is get the
undergrads to experience real research
and to learn. and that doesn't go away.
So, Europe should get stronger and
better than ever and you should not just
replace your Europs with an AI agent.
And that that I thought was brilliant,
too.
>> Yeah. Alex, your thoughts, please.
>> I think this falls under the category of
MIT should be careful what it wishes
for. I I think I I published I haven't
publicly circulated this, but wrote a a
mini manifesto called the endless
initiative. MIT has a history
approximately every two years of
launching some innovation initiative
usually to promote entrepreneurship or
something entrepreneurship adjacent to
MIT and they usually fall flat. I I
think the elephant in this particular
room, so it's the first time I'm
mentioning an elephant in this episode
for those tracking is that I is that
MIT, if it is to fully execute on the
vision laid out in this memo, will
require I I claim MIT becoming
essentially a for-profit because that's
where this all goes. It's one thing to
sort of generalize the Europe program to
subsume more of the undergraduate
experience. Remember MIT's motto is
men's at Manis. So what happens when the
men's part of men's atmanis is basically
been completely automated away by AI and
every student can take every problem set
and just get all the right answers for
free. Well, you go over to the manus
side until we have humanoid robots doing
everything which is only a few years out
anyway.
>> Yes.
>> But what does that look like? It looks
like a a site to Verer Vinci's Fast
Times at Fairmont High. looks like
students launching startups and having
transformative economic impacts from
their dorm rooms or otherwise. At which
point, what is the role left for MIT
from an educational perspective? MIT
starts to look like a venture capital
fund and maybe a bit of adult
babysitting and maybe a few other
things, but it becomes a much looser
aggregation of more for-profitesque
institutional incentives. So in summary,
I would say MIT should be careful what
it wishes for because ultimately if it
goes down this road and executes well, I
I foresee MIT and other institutions
that follow it,
>> this is my fever dream, becoming
for-profit public benefit corporations
that can be IPOed on the New York Stock
Exchange or the NASDAQ because that's
where they want to be.
>> I have two immediate answers to that,
Alex. I talked to Mark Orinberg, the
chairman of MIT about this a lot. And
and answer number one is if you look at
where AI is going in the very short term
with biotech, with nanotechnology, with
new physics, with new materials, huge
amount of physical lab space to generate
the data that then feeds back into the
AI and MIT has a massive amount of that
that'll be more important than ever in
the next few years. So really lean on
that as a reason for existence. All the
undergrads working in those labs are
hugely valuable to society. The
challenge is I was on a board call for
Laya this morning, right, which is
building a scientific super intelligence
and building a million square foot of
automated robotic labs driven by that
AI. I mean, and there are, you know, a
couple of different companies doing
this. They're going to run circles
around research labs with graduate
students, right? So, I mean, unless
you're giving that kind of capability to
your graduate students to direct the AI,
right? trying to, you know, have MIT
research compete with fully automated,
you know, uh, dark, you know,
roboticized AIdriven closed labs. Uh,
there's no competition.
>> Yeah, there's no competition. But that's
very similar to when, you know, MIT used
to have the amazing chip fabs, you know,
before chip fabs absolutely took off.
And you could build the best little
transistor VLSI chips in the world at
MIT. But then it became an industry and
Intel took it over and and you know put
thousand times more money behind it than
MIT could ever afford. But that didn't
change the fact that gallium arssonide
was still going on at MIT and then it
moves to photonics and it was so if you
look at what LILA's going to build like
don't compete with Laya move adjacent to
it to the areas that they're not doing
and that may be materials that may be
nano they're not doing carbon nanot
tubes. There's there's a there's so much
explosion in capability with AI in every
direction. There's no shortage of things
that you can do in those labs. I
>> I'll agree with both of you in this
case. So for let's just pick on MIT.no
for a minute. So MIT.no was uh broadly
credited as an initiative under MIT
president Rafael Refe. There's a bit of
backstory there that I think has never
been publicly disclosed. So I'll spend
30 seconds publicly disclosing from my
vantage point the backstory for MIT.no.
When I was an undergraduate at MIT, I
think I was sophomore or junior year,
uh, business week for whatever reason
decided to do a story on my nanotech
research. And then assistant department
head of MIT Core 6, electrical
engineering, computer science, saw the
business week story on, you know, what's
his undergrad doing over his summer,
summoned me to his office and asked me
what could MIT be doing to be more
competitive in nanotech and nanopab in
general. And I said, MIT needs its own
nano fab facility to be competitive.
Well, that assistant department head was
Raphael Refe who became president of
MIT. This became one of his signature
initiatives, MIT.no. I walk by MIT.no
every day with Lisa Sue's name on it.
And I see utilization rates relatively
low. It's this gorgeous gleaming
building with clean rooms on every
floor. But if you look inside, sorry,
you look inside at the clean rooms,
utilization is relatively low. It's
maybe like 20,
>> it's it's too clean for its own good.
And I would love to see MIT.no
being its like being utiliz utilized at
near 100%. I I think the best way to
make that happen is probably for MIT to
act a little bit more like uh Berkshire
Hathway type for-profit holding company
of all of these assets including onampus
nanopab facilities that could be better
externalized. Uh I think the point here
is we're going to have to reinvent high
school and college
>> period right uh secondary education
everything right you know so I'm
involved in a a program called TKS that
is is doing that at the high school
level they're going to be new college
programs and all of them fundamentally
come back to teaching the student
purpose I think students who don't have
a purpose in their life so they've got
intrinsic motivations don't have their
mindsets formed you uh teaching them AI
skills, entrepreneurial skills, and
having them start companies. I think
your thesis in high school and your
thesis in college should be the company
you built.
>> Can I do my little rant here?
>> Look, universities all started out as
divinity schools, right? All of them. Uh
MIT, a couple of the new ones, Leo, but
they all started out as as for
other than the ones that didn't.
>> Uh well, a couple didn't. Waterl didn't,
MIT didn't, but most most did
historically. Um, then they became job
schooling uh environments once the
industrial revolution hit. Certainly all
the older ones were divinity schools and
now they need to think redo it again
because education we've been doing for
the last few hundred years on the supply
side. You go learn a skill like a
doctor, an accountant, an engineer. Then
you go to the job market to try and find
demand for that supply side skill. Well,
we have the the halflife of a a skill
used to be 30 years and now it's like 3
years. We don't know what the demand is.
We have no idea what a job looks like in
5 years. So all the way from primary to
secondary to university. We have to redo
the whole stack to go through problem
solving side. Go to the demand side. Get
excited about a problem and then work on
that problem. And the way you think
about that problem will be how you
engage. This is such a big leap. I see
this report as kind of one ray of light
in the gloom of higher education
everywhere. It's definitely pointing at
the right direction. But the the ask of
the institution to make such a dramatic
change is I think too much for the
legacy because immune system in academia
is the second worst ever. Religion is
the worst. Healthcare is the third
worst. Corporate immune systems the the
fourth worst. So asking this to change
you have to do a new model at the edge
Peter like what you're doing or what
others are doing and then rebuild the
whole institution from there.
>> End of
rant.
Well, the other the other thing I talked
to Mark Orinberg about a lot is that,
you know, if you look at all the stories
at the front end of this podcast,
there's always a question of motivation.
You know, I'm about to go public. I'm
about what like am I really telling you
the truth? And the university needs to
be the source of truth in AI, especially
MIT, which is such a leader in the area.
And you know, for a while there, MIT got
into politics, which is hugely stupid.
you know, should not should be
completely politically neutral and
totally ethical with no motivations
other than the long-term good of
humanity. And you know, because it's
it's beautifully balanced. All countries
come to MIT. All ethnicities, all
religions, they're all weighted equally
across the world in this one place. And
so, if you want to deal with the ethics
of AI in a location, it can't be in a
for-profit company. It's far better done
at MIT than anywhere else. And that
gives it a a really valuable almost
almost you know un you just insanely
valuable purpose that it's irreplaceable
in society. And so if you can build on
the the necessity of the labs and the
necessity of that ethical role in the
center then you have a very very
important role going forward.
>> Everybody welcome to the health section
of Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know we talk about AI on this
Moonshot podcast all the time. One of
the most important things AI is going to
be able to do for you besides educating
your kids and helping you with your
taxes is making sure that you're living
a healthy lifestyle that you get a
chance to get to 100 plus. I'm here
today with Dr. Don Mucalem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
part of my medical team. Don, a
pleasure.
>> Great.
>> You know, the thing that people are
concerned about most about living to 100
or 120 is their cognitive abilities.
making sure they don't have dementia and
uh the numbers about dementia are
problematic. Uh can you share what
you've learned?
>> Such an important point and you're right
at Fountain Life, our members, the
number one thing people are most
concerned about is losing their brain
health, forgetting the name of their
child, forgetting the face of their
loved one. We know that when it comes to
dementia, the conservative estimates are
that 45% are entirely preventable. What
was amazing is with the advanced testing
we're doing at Fountain Life, one
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age.
>> Wow.
>> But what was really awesome is again
back to that prevention when we
partnered it with healthy living. This
gives me chills. Eating healthier,
moving our bodies, sleep, optimizing
sleep is so important. You know what we
saw? We saw that we improved that brain
age by 26%. That is a big big number to
show that the majority of those
individuals were able actually to
improve the brain age.
>> And one of the things I love about
Fountain is we're searching the world
for the best therapeutics, the best
approaches, and making sure we bring it
to our members. So if having healthy
brain function uh till 100 120 is
important to you, check out Fountain
Life. Go to fountainlife.com/per.
Make sure you become the CEO of your own
health. All right, now back to the
episode. I'm going to take us to our
final story also on education. Uh so
this is the impact of AI on education
really in secondary for our teens out
there. Uh so let me show you this chart.
Uh and it's a chart that shows that you
know the problem is in the f is not in
the future the problem is right now.
Right? So what you're looking at is an
OECD PISA score. PISA stands for program
for international student assessment. It
focuses on evaluating 15-year-olds
across advanced economies in reading,
math, and science. Reading and math are
roughly flat for years, and then they
start a sharp decline in most recent
assessments. Uh the steepest declines in
the history of the test. Science
declines too, not as much. You know, uh
obviously this starts before chat GPT
and probably due to smartphones and
social media that did the first damage.
So uh Vala Afghar uh who posted this
chart says it clearly quote what happens
when we stop reading and writing and we
start outsourcing our thinking. This is
what the MIT article called cognitive
surrender. Uh Salem I want to go to you
first on this one. Your thoughts. So you
could go down a hand ringing wo is us
type of thing where we're losing uh
cognitive ability, critical thinking
skills, which I think is a real problem.
You could look at it also on the
positive side, right? We we've spent the
last few hundred years highly training
up our cognitive abilities to do deep
problems like mathematics and and
accounting and engineering etc etc. But
as AI takes over a lot more of that
cognitive ability, uh maybe we don't
need to do that deep thinking uh and
have be have that deep deep deep
expertise. The generalist approach of
kind of thinking about what problems to
think about really become really come to
the four here. I note that more than
half the CEOs in Silicon Valley have a
liberal arts degree because thinking
about problems in different ways is the
biggest uh uh strength in that
particular role. So if you think about
it from that perspective, I don't see
this as a wo is us type of model. I
think of it as a natural progression. We
would expect to see this I would see if
there's a response much more verbal
challenging uh around a students
understanding of topics and can we get
that across in some decent way but I
would expect to see this given what's
happening in AI. Yeah, I I quoted you
yesterday, Salem, to my friends Lou and
Maymay. Uh, and I I said, you know, this
is the transition from human doing to
human being. I
>> I'll just comment that I would maybe be
more concerned if super intelligence
weren't advancing as quickly as it is.
The capabilities of frontier models are
increasing far more quickly than the
purported capabilities of humans are
decreasing. So this is if there even is
a problem at all which I don't think
there is uh open pens we don't hand
ringing that much over atrophying of
abilities for humans in the
industrialized west to be agricultural
workers that much closed pen
>> could you could you substitute mdash
instead of pren
>> yeah we'll delve into that so I I I
don't worry that much about it super
intelligence we're going to merge with
we're going to merge with super int
intelligence in a few years. This is at
most, even if there is a problem at all
here, which I don't think there is. It's
at most like a 2 to threeyear problem
until we have wearables and BCIs and
full human machine mergers that make
again any moral panic. Like I I think
one of the themes in my mind for this
episode is unnecessary moral panics.
Okay, so mini moral panic, falling test
scores in humans. But we're about to
merge with the machines, and the
machines that we merge with will be far
smarter than the humans, the biological
meatbody humans that were taking these
outdated tests. So, who cares?
>> I'm curious from our listeners, do you
want to merge with the machines? Uh, I
mean, it's an interesting thing, right,
when this becomes available and and you
know, you're the first person, Alex, I
talked to about this on the concept of
as we see escalating ASI, you know, we
humans are are flat if not sublinear. Do
we couple with the AI to be part of that
ascendancy?
>> Yeah, of course we do.
>> I think we need to at least many people
will choose to. Some people will choose
not to, but many for a variety of
reasons will choose to. And I think
that's a great outcome. Sorry, Seline.
>> No, no, I think this is exactly right.
Important point. Look, we've been doing
this for for thousands of years. David's
wearing spectacles. Technically, he's a
transhumanist, right? The minute you get
a vaccination as a child, you're
technically a cyborg. We've been using
machines to augment the human experience
and improve our lives from the beginning
of town. All of a sudden is a huge
acceleration of that.
>> It's funny. I I see it a totally
different way. But I'm surprised
actually surprised. You know, See, when
I see reading scores plummeting, I I
don't even go to this like, "Oh, who
cares? It may not even matter. We'll all
upload." I'm like, "No, this is like
fundamentally horrible." Like reading
scores are plummeting. This is bad. And
so it's obviously from social media, not
from AI, by the way. way
>> but look at the trajectory right like I
mentioned earlier the highest literacy
was like 200 years ago we've been
sliding down as a long trend ever since
then uh and you should expect it is as
you have much more capability of AI to
summarize things make sense of things
etc the question is what should we do as
a response to it because that's going to
happen anyway fighting for the raging
against the dying of the night uh with
our cognitive abilities against an AI
that can think faster with more access
to information is a losing battle. But
it goes to it goes to the being part
where where the human being becomes much
more uniquely qualified in the
experiential nature of being alive.
>> The headmaster of the school that my
kids went to for middle school used to
take everyone in the entire 7th grade
class to an island off the coast of
Maine with no phones. And they were
absolutely a gasast that they would have
to be disconnected for three days on an
island. and they came back the happiest
they'd ever been in their lives every
single year. And then they killed it
because they said it was inhumane to do
this. And so now they they've eliminated
it. But I'm like, you know, you don't
know what you haven't experienced. And I
worry a lot about, you know, a
generation growing up and say, "This is
fine. This there's nothing wrong with
the way I'm living. Yeah, I'm texting
every 5 seconds and I can't live
without." But I but it's fine. It's like
we haven't actually experienced the
opposite. And until you have, you don't
really have an opinion.
>> Our son goes to summer camp every summer
and they have no phones at the summer
camp. And when he comes back, he's the
most joyous human being for about 3 days
until he's back in his devices. Right.
>> You're not even you're not even texting
full sentences. You're
>> And I got
I got to give a shout out to Lily here
who made an unbelievable quote at this
parents event we got together. She says,
"When my kid has a device, I get 20% of
the kid. When he doesn't have a device,
I have 80% of the kid." and you're like,
"Wow,
pretty pretty telling commentary." But
the technology is going to move forward.
We have to integrate with it and then
reind our humanity in that context.
>> There there's a lot packed into that.
But I think we discovered in the 1960s
that we could create drugs that
everyone's like, "Yeah, this is fine."
And then they come out totally mangled
for life. You can do that with
electronics, too. And I I don't doubt
that something will come along very soon
in the age of AI that's as as addictive
as the worst drug ever created that's
equally mangling to the human being and
they come out less happy. The whole goal
here is to have really happy, really
healthy, infinite longevity people. And
that that's what we're after in this
entire endeavor. We're not building it
to to have the most addictive video game
in the history of the world and and walk
away from it depressed. That's not the
goal. Do you guys have time to speedrun
the AMA?
>> Yeah, I've got like seven minutes or so
I could do it real quick.
>> All right, let's do it. Uh, okay. I'm
gonna take the first one actually
because it's something Alex and I
disagree with. Is there such a thing as
intellectual property in the age of AI?
You know, we're going to have uh
Astroteller on stage with us at the
Moonshot Summit. I'm going to recall the
conversation I had with Tim and Steve
Jerbbertson in which at the end during
ASI, if there's a patent that's filed by
your competition, ASI is going to help
you work around it. And I think
intellectual property, while it's great,
we should keep going. It's going to have
far less value in the long run. That's
my opinion. I'm sticking with it. Alex,
you take the next one. Well, I'll offer
the 5-second rebuttal, which is anyone
who believes that, I invite you to
publish all of your private keys on the
internet. If if IP is dead, have at it.
Share your private keys.
>> Okay, I should have said patents, not
not intellectual property in in general.
>> Generated alternatives.
>> Um, okay. So, I I'll pick number four.
Could RSI bypass the need for massive
data centers entirely? How and when does
that happen? And this is from Tom
Monahan 8305. I think we're seeing micro
versions of this in the form of call
them deepseek moments where algorithmic
innovations from Chinese labs
temporarily but sharply reduce the need
for infrale compute. In the long term
jury is still out I think as to whether
the perfect model as I often think of it
like what is at the end of the RSI
rainbow. I I think I think it's very
likely that we will discover what the
perfect AI model looks like. The most
perfect use of flops or ops or whatever
the operative unit of compute ends up
being. It will be globally
mathematically provably optimal. And at
that point, I think we'll know whether
we need to keep doing this sort of
horizontal exponential buildout and
build the Dyson swarms or whether it's
just so perfect, so mathematically
perfect. Maybe there will be a physical
integration as well that we don't need
to disassemble our solar system. Maybe
there will be a physical integration.
Who knows? Maybe we'll find a way, say,
to leverage gravity as a substrate for
compute. Maybe we build a bunch of
microscopic black holes that do all of
our compute for us via RSI extending
downward into the physical layer. So we
don't need massive data centers anymore.
How and when does that happen? I I think
we'll know in at at most 10 years.
>> See, over to you.
>> I will take number two. What are the
ideal outcomes for the upcoming China US
summit? Um, you know, I would love a
practical agreement where that makes
dangerous incidents less likely. So, we
have a lot of shared interests, right?
Loss of control protecting
infrastructure. Uh, could you create
reliable communications channels? Could
you do incident reporting? Uh, shared
incident reporting. Those are the things
I'd love to see happen because there's
so much to work on to generate a
collective approach towards the world of
abundance than to fight about it. I I
don't believe that's going to happen,
but let's see.
>> All right, Dave, number three is for
you.
>> Number three. I'm glad I got number
three. I love this question. Do you
think there will come a time when we
have to pause AI just to understand it
because we'll have no idea what it's
talking about from Supreme Supreme King
Sovereign. That's a pretty bold name.
Um, so, uh, I love this question. You
know, at MIT, if you, um, if you get a
bunch of investors together at a
conference, they talk to each other and
have a blast and they share a lot of
knowledge. Then you get two physicists
together and you say, "Why don't you
guys talk to each other and share ideas
and have a blast?" And they have no idea
what each other are working on. They
literally like, "What?" And so they end
up talking about politics and sports the
whole time because um because the
knowledge gets so deep and so
disconnected. That's exactly what will
happen with AI. You know, everything we
build in society has a clean simplified
interface on top of it. Otherwise, you
can't build on top of it. And AI will be
the same way. it'll be solving very very
complicated things but giving it back to
us in very simple buildable uh API forms
or wrapper forms and so I think no is
the answer I think we'll we'll it'll
continually explain to us very clearly
what it discovered and what it what it
can do
>> all right I'm going to take number seven
here as we age longer what about organs
that keep growing from H said50 uh so50
uh go listen to the podcast I released
yesterday uh with Martin Rothblat uh
Martin is building a whole set of
replacement organs, heart, liver, lung,
kidneys, and thymus. I'm most excited
about thymus. You'll learn out why when
you go to that. So, uh, as we age
longer, we're going to have, you know,
not one, but probably four or five
different approaches to having a whole
set of replacement organs. Some of them
today, if they're generated from, uh,
you know, humanized pigs where you've
taken out the retroviruses and you
change the surface antigens, but you
still need imunosuppressants. The other
next generation is going to be from your
genome, your stem cells regrowing uh a
organ for yourself. It's like, you know,
you see all these Ford Model T's at car
shows that are still running around. Why
are they doing that? Because they've
replaced every part and we can do the
same thing at least for the moment
except for the brain uh in humans as
well. Uh Salem,
>> wait, that that Martin Rothblad
interview I just popped up on my feed
this morning. That is just brilliant.
Peter, if anyone has extra time this
afternoon,
>> definitely. No matter what you do,
you're going to be fascinated by this
interview. It's it's absolutely epic.
>> Thank you. It's a short one. It's 50
minutes. It's easily consumable during
your during your workout.
>> Um, what's your
>> Let me take the first one for number
five. When will AI when when will AI
develop genuine curiosity and could that
be the clearest time we reach AGI? And
that's from J2 C. Clearly a musical
mind. Um my preferred question would be
whether it helps us discover something
important that we would not have
investigated otherwise. That would be a
better framework. I think I don't I
think curiosity alone is not sufficient
as a test for AGI. You want transfer,
you want learning capability, you want
reliable action as a potential outcome.
I think there's a few other things that
uh um uh come up for me when you think
there's this. I'd look for uh
self-directed
uh work. Um um can you design sensible
experiments? All sorts of things come
up. Curiosity by itself. We could train
a system. Dave made this point earlier.
You could train an LLM to do pretty much
anything. You could train it to be to be
highly curious, which I think we should
do and will do. Uh but that doesn't for
me indicate AGI per se.
>> Okay, Alex, you want to take number
eight? Is that yours? I I feel like I
need to offer shorter answers, half
answers for six and eight with your
forbearance, Peter.
>> Yes. Okay. With if Dave if Dave can
layer on top.
>> Okay.
>> Very good. Dave, let let's split the
difference. So So six asks, "AI comes up
with solutions to math problems, but can
it discover new problems? Can it write a
new list of millennial problems?" This
is from Karen Ready. The answer is yes,
of course. Simple heristic for hard call
them millennium problems in math is can
the problem be very simply stated. So
minimizing the number of tokens for
stating it but then does the proof
require maximum tokens. So the
heruristic is you want to maximize
number of proof tokens divided by number
of problem statement tokens and AI can
absolutely generate lots of new
millennium style programs. They're not
scarce. Question eight asks
>> I think that's your I think that's your
next assignment Alex.
>> Stay tuned. Question eight asks what are
your thoughts on the connectto fruitfly?
This is from swing and steel 8519. And
so I I assume this is in reference to
the Google uploaded fruitfly. You'll
recall I'll cite to myself a number of
months ago a company that I helped found
Eon Systems announced the first
multibehavior fruitfly upload actually
beating by many months the Google
fruitfly upload. So I'm broadly
supportive of uploaded fruit flies. I
think we don't upload enough fruit
flies. I am not I I am not supportive of
torturing uploaded non-human animals.
So, I I wrote in my newsletter about
fruit flies that are being forced to day
trade Bitcoin. I am not supportive of
forcing fruit flies to be uploaded and
then day trade Bitcoin. Some of them
were being forced to play doom, I am not
supportive of forcing fruit flies to
play doom. But I I I do think that we
need to upload substantially all of our
biosphere. So to the extent that
uploaded fruit flies are treated well
and humanely or fruitfly, I think this
is terrific and we should do a lot more
of them.
>> Alex is the patron saint of uh of
>> Dave. You want to layer anything on top?
>> I'll just layer on to six. I I I agree
with Alex that AI will come up with
interesting Navier Stokes type problems.
But I if you go to the very top of the
pyramid fable 5.1 right now and just say
write me a really interesting
challenging problem as good as Navier
Stokes that's critical to the future of
humanity it will fail miserably on that
prompt which tells you a lot about the
role of coaching it. If you the
alternate approach is say give me 10,000
ideas and then give me a process for
whittling it down to the interesting
ones that will work better. it still
won't quite get you there, but that
shows you where we are with AI right
now. It's it's a really good question
and it it doesn't just happen magically
right now.
>> All right. Uh if you're a creative, uh
please send us your outro video. We'd
love it and love to show it. Uh a
pleasure to show this one. It's titled
Moonshots Most Amazing Time Alive by K
Bros. All right, guys. Enjoy this. We
stand at the edge of a brand new dawn. A
world once imagined is already on. A
massive tsunami is starting to ride. And
this is the most amazing
time to be alive.
Peter sees the map where the old lines
end. A builder, a scout, a guide, a
friend. From health to space, from cold
to sky. He walks all terrain with a
fearless side. Salon brings calm when
the stakes are high. A steady hand, a
reason why
you feel the future when he speaks. Not
loud, just strong. The kind that leans.
Dave is fire with a starship mind.
Contagious energy of the rarest kind.
Like Star Trek dreams made flesh and
sound. He lifts the room when he comes
around that keeps both feet on the
ground. Where truth and logic can be
found. A geek but real precise and
clear. We transform ideas into something
near
tomorrow in a deeper frame. System
signals a different game. A Star Trek
mind with a searching soul. Always
reaching for the larger hole. The wave
is coming wide and fast. Breaking open
limits from the past. No gate can hold
what light can see. Because intelligence
wants to be free.
Wants to be free. Flowing through minds
and humanity.
From a Dyson swarm to a healing light.
We turn possibility into the light. A
massive tsunami across the sky. And this
the most amazing
time
to be alive.
>> All right. Thank you, Kro.
>> Wow, that was good, Kro. That was that
was different and better and well
prompted.
>> Excellent.
>> Yeah, I love it.
>> Yeah.
>> All right, gentlemen. God Almighty, uh,
see you guys live in a week. Excited for
that.
>> All right.
>> It's going to be good.
>> Thank you, AWG. Safe flights home to
both of you. Dave, be well, my friend.
>> Thank you.